<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lifes brevitie and deaths debility Evidently declared in a sermon preached at the funerall of that hopeful and uertuous yong gentleman Edvvard Levvkenor esquire, &amp;c. In whose death is ended the name of that renowned family of the Lewkenors in Suffolke. By Tymothy Oldmayne minister of the Word of God at Denham in Suffolke. Our dayes on earth are as a shaddow, and there is none abiding. Also an elegy and an epitaph on the death of that worthy gentleman, by I.G. Dr. of D.</title>
            <author>Oldmayne, Timothy.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 163 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08482</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18806</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120802</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855995</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855995</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21508</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08482)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21508)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1212:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Lifes brevitie and deaths debility Evidently declared in a sermon preached at the funerall of that hopeful and uertuous yong gentleman Edvvard Levvkenor esquire, &amp;c. In whose death is ended the name of that renowned family of the Lewkenors in Suffolke. By Tymothy Oldmayne minister of the Word of God at Denham in Suffolke. Our dayes on earth are as a shaddow, and there is none abiding. Also an elegy and an epitaph on the death of that worthy gentleman, by I.G. Dr. of D.</title>
                  <author>Oldmayne, Timothy.</author>
                  <author>Garnons, John, fl. 1636.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 82, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by N. and I. Okes dwelling in little S. Bartholomewes neere the Hospitall gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1636.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I. G. = John Garnons.</note>
                  <note>Imprimatur is misdated 1625.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lewkenor, Edward, 1614-1634.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21508:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21508:1"/>
            <p>LIFES BREVITIE AND DEATHS Debility.</p>
            <p>Evidently Declared in a Sermon Preached at the Funerall of that Hopeful and Uertuous yong Gentleman EDVVARD LEVVKENOR Eſquire, &amp;c. <hi>In whoſe Death is ended the name of that renowned Family of the</hi> Lewkenors <hi>in Suffolke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Tymothy Oldmayne</hi> Miniſter of the Word of God at <hi>Denham</hi> in <hi>Suffolke.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Our dayes on Earth are as a ſhaddow, and there is none abiding.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Alſo an <hi>Elegy</hi> and an <hi>Epitaph</hi> on the death of that worthy Gentleman, by <hi>I. G. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi> of <hi>D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>N.</hi> and <hi>I. Okes</hi> dwelling in little S. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholmewes</hi> neere the Hoſpitall gate. 1636.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:21508:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>FLECTAR NON FRANGAR</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21508:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFULL AND Of high Deſert, the Lady MARY <hi>Lewkenor</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> 
               <hi>Elizabeth Lewkenor,</hi> the Mother and ſorrowfull Widdow of this Deceaſed Gentleman: together with the right worſhipfull and truly noble Lady, the Lady <hi>Anne Le-ſtrange</hi> Wife to Sir <hi>Nicholas Le-ſtrange</hi> Baronet: As alſo to her two vertuous and worthy ſiſters, Miſtris <hi>Katherine</hi> and Miſtris <hi>Mary Lewkenor,</hi> Eternall Happineſſe, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oth I am (right <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull</hi> and truely <hi>Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi>) that this rough &amp; unpoliſhed diſcourſe of mine, ſhould unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately renew Your former griefe, or fill thoſe Eyes againe with <hi>teares,</hi> which were never fully dried ſithence
<pb facs="tcp:21508:50"/>
this heavy <hi>Accident befell this Noble Plant,</hi> ſo neere, ſo deere unto you. For ſorrow <hi>(I know right well)</hi> is of a quick and apprehenſive <hi>nature,</hi> &amp; that the leaſt touch maketh the <hi>Veſſell eaſily o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verflow.</hi> How ever, <hi>I humbly intreate,</hi> that mine <hi>innocency herein,</hi> may <hi>anſwer</hi> for me: my ayme beeing chiefly this, <hi>to ſtrew onely ſome few flowers upon the Hearſe of this my honourable friend,</hi> ſuch as in his life time, his owne Hand <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered,</hi> pleaſant unto the <hi>Eye,</hi> and of a moſt odoriferous <hi>Sent.</hi> Neither is this <hi>Treatiſe of mine</hi> otherwiſe inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but to bee a true <hi>Remembrancer,</hi> to tell ſucceeding <hi>Ages</hi> the greatneſſe <hi>of the loſſe;</hi> when your renowned Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, was by the Untimely <hi>Death</hi> of this ſo Hopefull a Young <hi>Gentleman,</hi> thus fatally ſmitten, if not quite over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned.
<pb facs="tcp:21508:50"/>
This <hi>Towne</hi> which now af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordeth me my being, formerly affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded mee my firſt <hi>breath.</hi> And foure generations of your honourable <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily,</hi> haue I ſeene here upon the <hi>Stage,</hi> ſucceſſiuely <hi>acting</hi> their ſeveral <hi>Parts. Angels</hi> and <hi>Men</hi> were the lookers on, and with great applauſe, highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended their true <hi>Action,</hi> &amp; generous <hi>demeanour.</hi> But now alas, the <hi>Theater</hi> is wholy empted, and all the <hi>Actors</hi> quite gone, the <hi>Stage</hi> hourely expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be pulled down; and if it ſtand, yet little hope there is that ever our eyes <hi>ſhall ſee</hi> ſuch <hi>Actors</hi> any more up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, to play their parts ſo commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, as thoſe Antients did. The conſideration whereof, as it carrieth with it not onely trouble, but indeed a kind of <hi>amazement,</hi> ſo is there much
<pb facs="tcp:21508:3"/>
               <hi>wiſedom</hi> required in cenſuring and <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience</hi> in induring what is <hi>hapned.</hi> My humble requeſt therfore <hi>(unto you right Worſhipfull)</hi> is, as thoſe that haue the greateſt <hi>ſhare</hi> in this unvaluable loſſe, that in the middeſt of ſo many diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Thoughts in ſearching out the true cauſe and end that the Almighty hath in doing this, you would be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to remember theſe three Things: Firſt, that there is in <hi>God</hi> an unboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>will,</hi> that his <hi>Judgements</hi> are <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable,</hi> and his <hi>Waies</hi> paſt finding out. Secondly, that <hi>You</hi> would bee pleaſed to looke backe upon the <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe,</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> of your Family, <hi>which</hi> formerly, <hi>You</hi> have both ſeene and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted. Beleeve mee, <hi>right worſhipfull,</hi> the ſight thereof will be a Soveraigne preſervatiue againſt <hi>Repining.</hi> Laſtly,
<pb facs="tcp:21508:3"/>
that ſeeing it was determined, by an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, and inevitable <hi>decree</hi> (that the Sirnames of your Family, <hi>ſhould</hi> heere fatally end) that you would bee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſolace and <hi>cheriſh</hi> your Hearts, that it is done without the leaſt ſpot and <hi>blemiſh</hi> to the ſame. And that this young <hi>Gentleman</hi> ſo honourably concluded, and cloſed up all ſo happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as Hee hath done, to his immortall praiſe.</p>
            <p>But I deſire not to tell the Travai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler the way hee knoweth ſo well al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready; or light a Candle when the Sunne is up, or leade the hand of the skilfull Artiſt. Here therefore I doe humbly take my leaue, deſiring You to accept of what is done heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as the Fruite of that unfeigned Loue, and dutiful Reſpect which <hi>was</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21508:4"/>
alwayes borne by him, to your Honourable and worthy Family, who ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in the Lord to be commanded to the uttermoſt of his power untill Death:</hi> Tymothy Oldmayne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <p>Perlegi concionem hanc cui titulus eſt <hi>(Lifes brevity)</hi> in qua nihil reperio quo minus cum utili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate publica imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ex aedib. Fulham. decimo die</hi>
                  <date>Septem. <hi>1625.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>SA: BAKER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21508:4"/>
            <head>LIUES BREVITY, AND DEATHES DEBILITY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ISAIAH 26. VERS. 19.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Thy dead men ſhall live; with my dead body ſhall they ariſe: awake and ſing yee that dwell in the duſt; for thy dew is as the dew of Herbes, and the earth ſhall caſt out the dead.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T would have brought much eaſe and comfort to our ſorrowfull hearts, if we had only heard of this ſad accident, (the death I mean of this ſo noble a Plant, this Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable young <hi>Gentleman</hi>) and not beene Eye-witneſſes of the ſame. And that the ſame Countrie which received his laſt breath, had likewiſe imbraced his honourable Aſhes: his living preſence how welcome would it have been unto us? But comming thus amongſt us ſhrouded under the blacke mantle of death! we tremble at it:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21508:5"/>
For this is one of the miſeries of man (when death ſeizeth on him) that he that was neereſt unto him in affection; then deſireth to bee fartheſt from him in action: and that living face, that affoorded greateſt joy; when once dead, carrieth with it greateſt terrour, neither can the concluſion of all this ſad <hi>Cataſtrophe,</hi> but adde vineger to our bleeding wound, that whilſt we were ſeriouſly bethinking with our ſelves, in what ſort wee may beſt expreſſe the inward griefe and trouble of mindes for this our loſſe, in doing all the honour that poſſibly wee could unto him, in this his Funerall obſequies: Lo, the tediouſneſſe of the way, and terribleneſſe of the diſeaſe, had ſo ſhattered and cruſhed that tender, and delicate body of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming along to us, riding in that dolfull Chariot of death; that no ſooner had a few teares given him a ſad welcome, but we were enforced to give his body to the earth, and we to him a ſorrowfull Adieu.</p>
            <p>But in all this, patience muſt poſſeſſe our ſoules: And ſeeing he is now already entred into the houſe of his age, and ſweetly ſleepeth upon his bed of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, amongſt the reſt of his noble. Anceſtors: let us I pray you turne our thoughts awhile from him, and looke a little upon the hand of God; in doing this to him: and with him in cutting off (as it were with one ſtroake) the name and glory of ſo renowned a family amongſt us. To that end it muſt be remembred, as a thing not wholy paſt the memory of man: how the Grand-father of this young Gentleman (of high repute) joyning himſelfe in marriage with a Right Worſhipfull family in this County, left that former feate and dwelling of that ancient family of his owne
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21508:5"/>
in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and building up his name amongſt us, by his noble and vertuous demeanour, became a grace and ornament, both to this obſcure Village wherein wee now live, as alſo to the whole Countrie round about. And ſo like a glorious ſtarre ſhining long amongſt us, at length yeelded to nature in his old age and fulneſſe of dayes: Him a bleſſed Sonne ſucceeded, an Heire to his Fathers Lands, and an inheritour of his Fathers beſt and choyſeſt vertues:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.16</note> Such being the ornaments and rich endowments of his minde, that had the right hand of wiſedome beene as bountifull to him, as her left hand was: we queſtionleſſe ſhould have deemed him borne to be admired. But (alas) he dyed in the middeſt of his dayes, and chiefeſt of his Honours. Laſt of all, this hopefull young Gentleman, in time, followed: a <hi>Phoenix</hi> in our daies, but cruſhed in the ſhell: a pleaſant Flower, but killed in the Spring; a noble plant, but of yeſterdayes continuance, and ſent for a time amongſt us, only to be loved, deſired, and lamented. Here you ſee are three generations onely; and thoſe three are al: for with this latter, the fountaine dried, and with his death the name of the <hi>Lewkenors</hi> in <hi>Suffolke,</hi> is quite extinguiſhed.</p>
            <p>A lamentable thing to behold ſo flouriſhing a <hi>Caedar</hi> ſo ſuddainely to fade, and within the memory of man, ſo worthy a family to be both begun and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 29 15 <hi>Iob.</hi> 8.9.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.1.11</note> But here wee ſee the fraile condition of all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine fleſh: A Breath: a Bubble: the houſe of the ſpider; frailer then the graſſe, and more uncertaine then the flower of the field: according to that 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.14. <hi>All fleſh is graſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.14</note> And heere againe wee ſee what the houſes and habitations of the mighty
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21508:6"/>
are if the angry breath of God bloweth on them: today mine, to morrow thine, &amp; the next day God knoweth whoſe. Here, laſtly we ſee the reaſon why <hi>Solomon</hi> the wiſe, making choyce of the rareſt and chiefeſt flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers here below, moſt delightfull to the heart of man (as Honours, Riches, large Fields, faire Poſſeſſions, young yeares, and youthful daies, intending with the ſame (as it ſeemeth) a wreath or garland, to adorne his Crowne and Scepter) whilſt he houldeth them in his hand, he loatheth them, and caſting them from him, he cryeth out as he doth;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.2</note> 
               <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Vanity of vanities all is vanity.</hi> And no marvell, for all theſe cannot keep off the ſtroake of death, or preſerve a man from the power of the grave.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 49.15</note>
            </p>
            <p>Oh that all ſorts of men, of what degree ſo ever, high or low, that ever heard of this Gentlemans un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely death, would likewiſe harken to him, whilſt with deaths dreaded Trumpet ſet to his pale (yet bleſſed) lips, he thus calleth to them.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Firſt my honourable friends and equals, my ſociats and companions: Loe here in me you ſee your ſelves: my lot to day;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 52.7 <hi>Iob</hi> 30.25 <hi>Pro.</hi> 31.30 <hi>Jere.</hi> 9.23 <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.10</note> yours perhaps to morrow: truſt not (I beſeech you) in Riches, Beauty, Strength, or in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of your Age: for they are things more brittle then Ice. I had them al, and loe yee ſee how ſuddenly I have loſt them. I leaned a little too hard on them: and ſee like an <hi>Egyptian-reed;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 36 6</note> how trecherous in the end I found them. Sweete companions are they in the time of health;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 16.2</note> but miſerable comforters at the houre of death.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.33</note> Haſten therefore your peace with God, and as ſoone as may bee make him your friend: ſo when all things elſe doe faile you, hee will not forſake you: for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21508:6"/>
he hath ſaid it (and by ioyful experience I have found it) <hi>I will not faile thee, nor forſake thee.</hi> Yea,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joſu.</hi> 1.5 <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.6</note> when all friends leave you, then will he be neareſt to you. <hi>Holding you by the right hand, and ſaying:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa</hi> 41.13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Feare not, feare not, thou worme,</hi> Iacob, <hi>I will helpe thee ſaith the Lord, thy redeemer, the holy one of</hi> Iſrael.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And you my loving friends, men of lower ranke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146 3, 4, 5</note> 
                  <hi>my ſorrowfull neighbous and the reſt, to you I onely ſay:</hi> Truſt not in man, nor in the ſonne of man:<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 32.8 <hi>Ier.</hi> 17.5</note> neither build your hope upon the arme of fleſh: for the greateſt Prince his breath is in his noſtrils, and when he dyeth his thoughts periſh. <hi>Had you truſted more in God, and leſſe in mee; God it may bee, would have truſted you longer with me: but you robbing him of his right, he hath juſtly deprived you of your comfort. He onely is the bleſſed man:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.7, 8</note> That truſteth in the Lord, and whoſe hope the Lord is. For hee ſhall be as a tree planted by the waters, that ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth her rootes by the river, and ſhall not ſee when heate commeth, but his leafe ſhall bee greene, and ſhall not faile in the yeare of drought, neither ſhall ceaſe from yeelding fruit.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Theſe with many other; the like neceſſary, and profitable inſtructions, this ſweet young Gentleman with his dying breath, proclaimeth to us: the which for brevities ſake I am inforced to omit, leaving them wholy to the due conſideration of every Chriſtian: And come now to take the ſhort ſurvey of his life and death, full of grace and exceeding commendable. The which before I can with any convenience doe, I muſt here ſtay a while and anſwere a maine Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21508:7"/>
which like another wounded <hi>Amaſa</hi> lying tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling in our way,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20 12</note> hindreth us from proſecuting our intended courſe with that cheerefulneſſe that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we might.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> The Objection ariſeth altogether from Gods dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with this Honourable, and Religious family, in thus cutting off the name and poſterity thereof.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 12.7</note> For Wiſedome ſaith.<hi>Prov.</hi> 12.7. <hi>The wicked are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, and are not: but the houſe of the righteous ſhall ſtand.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.2, 3</note> And David ſaith, <hi>Pſal</hi> 112.2, 3. <hi>His ſeed ſhall be mighty upon earth: the generation of the upright ſhall be bleſſed. Wealth and riches ſhall be in his houſe: and his righteouſneſſe endureth for ever.</hi> And <hi>Eliphaz</hi> ſaith, <hi>Iob.</hi> 22. <hi>ver.</hi> 23.24. <hi>If thou returne to the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 22.23 24.</note> 
               <hi>and ſhalt put away iniquity farre from thy Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. Then ſhalt thou lay up Gold as duſt, and the Gold of</hi> Ophir <hi>as the ſtones of the brookes: Yea the Almighty ſhall be thy defence: and thou ſhalt have plenty of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi> But heere wee ſee the quite contrary: for in ſtead of gathering here is ſcattering: in ſtead of buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding up, heere is pulling downe: in ſtead of plenty, here is ſcarcity: in ſtead of fulneſſe here is emptines. Againe wee read in holy writ of a reward of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, <hi>Math.</hi> 6. Yea here in this life, <hi>Math.</hi> 19.29. They ſhall receive an hundred fold. And is this the reward of the righteous,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3</note> to have their names written in the duſt, and their glorious Lampe quite put out? what is become of all the Prayers, Almes, and many pious and charitable actions, performed by his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Anceſtors? their gracing of true Religion with a moſt holy life and converſation? what is all come to this? All loſt and gone?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21508:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>For anſwere of all theſe,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere </seg>
               </label> firſt it muſt be held as an infalliable ground: a truth without all contradiction which the preacher delivereth.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecleſ.</hi> 2.16</note> As the wiſe man dyeth, ſo dyeth the foole: neither, Is love and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to be diſcerned by any outward thing whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecleſ.</hi> 9.2</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that as there are periods of Kingdomes: ſo are there of private and particular families. It was a queſtion, that <hi>Pompey</hi> once propounded to a certain Philoſopher, a ſage wiſe man of thoſe times (having lately before received by <hi>Caeſar</hi> an unrecoverable loſſe and overthrow) why <hi>Caeſar</hi> having ſo bad a cauſe in hand, and himſelfe ſo good; yet <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſhould ſo mightily prevaile as he did, and he fall in his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous cauſe more and more under his adverſaries victorious ſword? My Lord (anſwered he) <hi>Sunt periodi Regnorum</hi> there are periods of Kingdomes; and it is probable that the period of the Roman State is come to an end; and that the manner of the preſent government wil ſuddenly be changed; as not long after it came to paſſe. And ſo may I truely ſay by experience of particular families that they have their periods and one family paſſeth, and another commeth in the place thereof. Shew me elſe what is become not onely of thoſe holy families of which we have ſuch honourable mention in holy writ: but alſo of thoſe families of whom Heathen records ſpeake ſo honourably? The <hi>Syrgij, Appij, Fabij, Valerij, Bruti,</hi> and the like, that ſtood ſo much upon their Gentility, and eminents of blood, contemning all others, as <hi>Novi homines,</hi> new upſtarts in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of themſelves? If Families have not their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riods:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21508:8"/>
when we ſee it hourely before our eyes, this family cut off, and another comming in the place thereof: one ending and another beginning: ſo that what is come to this, is befalne to millions before; neither is it a new thing under the Sunne.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.9</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, it muſt be remembred, that Almighty God paſſeth none of his promiſes, but upon a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold condition.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. His Glory: then</item>
               <item>2. The good of the party.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Now God alwayes glorifies himſelfe two wayes:
<list>
                  <item>1. In his Mercy.</item>
                  <item>2. In his Juſtice.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in his mercy, in ſhowring downe his richeſt bleſſings upon the Houſe and Family of the righteous man;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pal</hi> 85.10</note> ſo that within the wals therof, mercy and truth do daily meete, righteouſneſſe and peace do kiſſe and imbrace one another. Yea, thoſe that by continuance in well doing, ſeeke glory, and honour, and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality: Eternall life is (ſayth the Apoſtle.) <hi>Glory and honour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.10</note> 
               <hi>and peace, to the Iew firſt, and alſo to the Greek.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in Juſtice in viſiting of ſinne with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall eye; not onely on the Fathers, but likewiſe on their children: yea oftimes ſo hotly, that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinneth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.22</note> and the child ſuffereth. <hi>The Fathers eat ſower grapes: &amp; the childrens teeth are iuſtly ſet on edge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, for the good of the party.</p>
            <p>And here it muſt be remembred, that it is a thing moſt uſuall with God our heavenly Father (intending the good of his ſervants: partly for their bodies, but principally for their ſoules) in diſpoſing of theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21508:8"/>
things, for ſpeciall reaſons beſt knowne unto himſelfe, to ſeeme after a ſort to croſſe his own word and promiſe made unto them. So that whereas hee promiſeth health, they meete with ſickneſſe, length of dayes, ſhortneſſe of Life: the Sunne ſhine of proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity, and behold they meete the ſad and gloomy dayes of adverſity: yea, it is ordinary with him to diſpoſe of all ſublunary bleſſings, as Queene <hi>Heſter</hi> for a time beſtowed her chiefeſt favours, not upon them ſhee loved beſt; but upon him ſhee hated moſt. For whereas <hi>Mordecay,</hi> her Uncle, and other her kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and neereſt alliance were ſeldome named, or it may be hardly looked on, (as may without wronging the text,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heſt.</hi> 2.10 20</note> not unprobably be gathered) <hi>Haman</hi> that cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Tyger, and bloody enemy to her ſtock and Nation, hath in the meane while, what heart could wiſh; and all the honour done him, which ſo mighty a Princeſſe could poſſibly beſtow uppon one that was her vaſſall and inferiour. Or like olde <hi>Iſaac's</hi> dealing with his two ſonnes, <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> making on a Lord, and cockering him under his Wing: and the other (the true heire of the promiſe) he turneth out of his doores with his ſtaffe in his hand, to ſeeke him a ſervice,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.1, 2, 3.</note> upon which hee might afterwards live by the ſweate of his browes.</p>
            <p>Many more inſtances of Gods dealing with his children in this kinde I could produce, which for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity ſake I doe heere omit: onely I could wiſh wee finding Almighty God walking in this ordinary way and courſe of his, that wee ſhould not by our uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable ſurmiſes, and raſh concluſions, eyther too rigidly cenſure his righteous actions; or meaſure at all
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21508:9"/>
his bleſſed ſteppes, by the rule and compaſſe of our ſhallow reach; remembring that there are <hi>Arcana Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videntiae,</hi> ſecrets and myſteries of Divine providence, into which, with the ſtrength of our dazled eye, wee are no way able at all to pierce.</p>
            <p>So that we may thinke, yea, verily beleeve this or that to be the true cauſe and reaſon of this, or the like heavy accident, and yet be nothing ſo, but a meere phantaſie of our owne. And truely this have others done before us, (ſtanding upon Record in holy writ) who verily beleeved they had as ſure a ground to walke upon; and as much reaſon to judge in divers caſes, as we poſſibly can haue, and yet when matters came to ſcanning, were miſerably deceived. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, to take 2. or 3. examples (amongſt many) who would not have judged the blindneſſe of that poore man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 9</note> who wanting ſight from his birth, and never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the <hi>Sun</hi> walking in his ſtrength, had bin either for his owne, or the ſin of his parents? and this was the opinion of moſt, as may appeare by the Diſciples words after.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.2, 3</note> 
               <hi>Maſter, who did ſin, this man, or his parents, that he was borne blind?</hi> But Chriſt tels another reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the verſe following. <hi>Neither this man, nor his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents:</hi> but the true cauſe (ſaith hee) is this: <hi>that the workes of God ſhould be made manifeſt in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or ſecondly, who would not have thought that the true reaſon, why <hi>Almighty</hi> God ſhortned (as hee did) the dayes and life of that young noble Prince, the hope of the ten <hi>Tribes,</hi> and honor of the houſe of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam,</hi> had beene the fierceneſſe of his wrath bent againſt that ungodly Family, for the horrible abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations daily therein committed; but it is not the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21508:9"/>
reaſon, that is alleadged by the Prophet, but it is the goodneſſe of the vertuous Prince (as hee affirmeth) that occaſioneth his untimely death: For ſo ſaith the Prophet <hi>Ahijah</hi> to the wife of <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> masking her ſelf in the weeds of another.<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 21 13.</note> 
               <hi>Get thee to thine owne houſe, and when thy feete enter into the City, the childe ſhall dye, and all Iſrael ſhall mourne for him, and bury him: for he onely of Ieroboam ſhall come to the grave, becauſe in him is found ſome good thing toward the Lord God in the houſe of Ieroboam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, who would not have thought but ſome one or other ſinne committed by himſelfe, or ſome of his Anceſtors, had been the cauſe why <hi>Ioſiah</hi> the mirrour of Kings, fell in battaile in the flower of his dayes by the ſword of <hi>Pharao Necho,</hi> King of <hi>Egypt.</hi> True it is, that ſin was one cauſe, and a maine one, for ſin cauſeth every calamity, (as the diſtemper of humours, every ordinary Ague) but this was not the true cauſe,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 35.25</note> and end that God aymed at, in his ſuddaine death: but that by this means he being the ſooner freed from trouble and vexation of heart, might enter his grave in peace,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay.</hi> 57.1</note> and might not ſee the evill to come. From all which examples, two things by the way offer themſelves unto us, worthy of our due conſideration.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, that men in cenſuring Gods heavy cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſements, lightning on the backs of the righteous, do uſually miſſe the true, and right end, in infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of the ſame, taking them as fiery <hi>Scorpions</hi> of his wrath; when as they are indeede, the fruites of his Fatherly affection toward them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That when Almighty God performeth not his promiſe to his children, in regard of outward bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings; then his uſuall manner is to provide
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21508:10"/>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>Better things for them.</hi> For inſtance, when he denieth them this outward traſh, and tranſitory ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, to give them Riches never fading, but alwaies bloſſoming. Hee denieth them outward comfort, and filleth their ſoules with glee and mirth. They weepe for a time, and laugh eternally.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, hence we may learne, to be very wary how wee doe raſhly paſſe our Verdicts in caſes of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for feare, leaſt miſſing Gods ayme, wee over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoot our ſelues, and highly offend. But above all, that we take heed of playing the <hi>Cantharides</hi> or ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king flye, where wee ſee the leaſt skinne off, there to bee ſucking and opening agayne the skars and blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, that were long ſince healed with the blood of Chriſt: Crying out with thoſe clamorous <hi>Iewes, Men of Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act</hi> 21.28</note> 
               <hi>theſe be the men:</hi> ſo wee, theſe are the ſinnes; that have procured wrath, and undone this Family. Nay <hi>brethren,</hi> let us rather hearken to <hi>Davids</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 41.1.2. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that conſidereth wiſely of the poore, the Lord ſhall deliver him in the time of trouble.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Colo.</hi> 3.14.</note> And to that ſweete counſell, that the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi> giveth, <hi>Above all things my brethren (ſayth hee) let us put on love, which is the bond of perfectneſſe.</hi> So ſhall wee with her faire mantle, not onely <hi>cover a multitude of ſinnes:</hi> but conſtrue things in a better ſenſe,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Peter</hi> 4</note> drawing our concluſions, not from hatred, but from a far milder Roote: namely</p>
            <p>From the loue of God,
<list>
                  <item>1. To this young Gentleman him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</item>
                  <item>2. In him, to us all.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <list>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21508:10"/>
               <item>1
<list>
                     <item>1 To him.
<list>
                           <item>1
<list>
                                 <item>1. In taking this noble plant, from the evil to come.
<list>
                                       <item>1. Of ſinne.<note place="margin">
                                             <hi>Iſay</hi> 57.1</note>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2 Of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2
<list>
                                 <item>2. In providing for him a Richer, and more noble inheritance, even the <hi>ſure mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of David. Iſay</hi> 55.3.<note place="margin">
                                       <hi>Iſay</hi> 55.3</note>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2
<list>
                     <item>2. <hi>To us all;</hi> if fairely we can draw honie out of the Eater; and wholſome inſtruction out of the dead carkaſſe of this dead Lyon: as God grant wee may.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Fourthly, it muſt bee remembred, that though the name of the Family in <hi>Suffolke,</hi> bee quite extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, yet that the Family it ſelfe is not (bleſſed bee the name of God) utterly deſtroyed. It is falne here; but it flouriſheth elſewhere. For amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other outward bleſſings, wherewith <hi>Almighty God</hi> marvailouſly enriched the <hi>Grand-father</hi> of this young Gentleman, he added that of <hi>Ioſephs;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen</hi> 49 25</note> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Vbertatem uberum &amp; vulvae:</hi> the bleſſing of the breaſts, and of the wombe: So that hee had <hi>Nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſam prolem,</hi> plenty of children, two Sonnes, and ſeaven daughters, a goodly off ſpring; and which increaſeth more the bleſſing, not one of them but was the choiſeſt ſhaft of a thouſand. Certainly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.</note> he need not be a ſhamed: <hi>For he might ſpeak boldly with his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy in the gate.</hi> Now in the younger ſonne of that honourable Knight (younger) I meane, then his <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> but deſerving indeede the Elders place in any Family of his degree) is the ancient and Worſhipfull name of this Family ſtill continued: and beeing rich in Sonnes, with the Favour of the <hi>Almighty</hi> is like, for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21508:11"/>
many ages ſo to bee. And beſides, it is the maſculine, and manly blood of the <hi>Lukenors</hi> onely heere in <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke;</hi> which by the untimely fall of this flouriſhing branch, is thus periſhed as wee ſee, and quite dryed up: otherwiſe much of that honourable blood run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth yet along (although in a milder ſtraine) through the pure veines of thoſe three truely vertuous Siſters, no waies inferiour to thoſe daughters of <hi>Zelophehad:</hi> yea,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 27.1</note> beſides theſe, there is a little <hi>Ruth</hi> left, a pledge of his love to his deare wife, and now ſorrowfull wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, who, although a daughter, yet by the pious and religious education of that wiſe and vertuous Gentlewoman (her mother) wee are to hope, will in Gods good time, build up againe this decayed and ſhattered family of <hi>Elimelech.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, and laſtly, to cloſe up all in a word, we muſt not be ignorant, how that moſt of the richeſt promiſes which our heavenly father hath in his great love and free mercy made to his deareſt children, are not uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and ordinarily fulfilled here in this life. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they are, but commonly they are not: and if they be, yet but in part, for the full recompence is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved till afterwards.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> And if it were not ſo, of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (ſaith the Apoſtle) we are moſt miſerable, as the truth is, they had bin. Their holineſſe and piety being accompted no better then madneſſe and folly, and their whole religion, <hi>Exitiabilem ſuperſtitionem, unde cuncta atrocia et pudenda confluunt:</hi> A damnable ſuperſtition; and the mother of all villany.</p>
            <p>And that we may ſee this yet the better, let us, I pray you, look a little into the lives of ſome few (omitting multitudes) of the choyſeſt ſervants of God, and ſee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21508:11"/>
their reward heere in this world. And firſt <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> a great Prophet, and one of a moſt auſtere life, and unſpotted converſation, the fore-runner and bright morning ſtarre, making way for the <hi>Sunne</hi> of righteouſneſſe ariſing in his full ſtrength: what was the reward he reaped for all his preaching, and paines taking in the Church of God, his thundring out of judgements againſt the wicked, without all partiality, and promiſing mercies to the true penitent and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſoule? ſurely to have his head ſtruck off from his ſhoulders at the command of an arrant ſtrumpet, and his body to be caſt forth as dung upon the earth: onely here was his comfort,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.40</note> that at the laſt he ſhould not looſe the reward of a Prophet, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.40.</p>
            <p>Againe what was the reward of them of whom we have ſuch honourable mention<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.38</note> whoſe names deſerve golden letters, perſons of whom the world was not worthy, ſurely after all their fruites of a lively faith, their love, their zeale, their conſtant confeſſion of the name of Chriſt; was it not to be tryed with cruell mockings, and ſcourgings, to be tortured and horribly tormented, to be ſawne aſſunder &amp; ſlaine with the Sword? Only here was their comfort, that in the end they ſhould obtaine a ioyfull reſurrection.</p>
            <p>What laſtly was that reward of that good Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. after hee had with a deale of care and trouble, not onely reformed many diſorders and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes in the Church and publicke ſtate, but alſo had mightily daunted and brought under, the haughty courage of the <hi>Guelph's</hi> faction. But at laſt, to be poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned (at the receiving of the bleſſed <hi>Sacrament</hi>) with an invenomed Hoſt, which a traiterous &amp; deteſtable
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21508:12"/>
monke of the order of St. <hi>Dominicke</hi> gave unto him: the which Fact of this bloody Monſter, as it ought of every Loyall heart to bee abhorred and deteſted, ſo ought the Patience, and aſſured confidence of this moſt Chriſtian Emperour, to be highly Magnified, and to the Heavens extolled: who as the ſtory ſaith, finding the poyſon (immediately uppon the receite thereof) working in his bowels, and thereupon death approaching, commanded inſtantly the Villaine to bee brought before him; and thus without all paſſion ſpake unto him: <hi>Tu calicem vitae invertiſti mihi in mortem: quare o Domine fuge celeriter; nam ſi inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci, &amp;c.</hi> O fayth hee, thou haſt turned to me, the cup of Life, into the cup of Death: Wherefore flye; for if our Friends lay hold on you, you are ſure to dye a moſt miſerable death: and repent you. <hi>Ego enim moriar ſecundum voluntatem Domini: tu vas ira fui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti, &amp;c.</hi> It is the will of God, that I ſhould die this kinde of death; but thou haſt beene the Veſſel of his wrath unto me, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By all which examples (omitting thouſands) it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth plainely, that the principall reward is reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved till afterward: and hitherto ſerve theſe and the like comfortable promiſes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10</note> 
               <hi>Be faithfull unto Death; and I will give thee a Crowne of Life. And</hi> againe, <hi>To him that overcommeth, will I grant to fit with mee in my throne, even as I overcame, and ſit with my Father in his throne. And Chap.</hi> 22.12. <hi>Behold, I come ſhortly, and my Reward is with me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.6</note> 
               <hi>And, Who will render to every man according to his workes.</hi> The trueth of all which, apprehended by a lively Faith, maketh the bleſſed <hi>Apoſtle Paul,</hi> to cry out with that plerophory,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21508:12"/>
and full aſſurance that he doth. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7.8</note> 8 <hi>Certa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men illud praeclaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> decertavi, curſum conſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mavi, fidem ſervavi. Hactenus, &amp;c. I have fought a good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the faith. Hence forth there is laid up for me a Crowne of righteouſneſſe, which the Lord the righteous Iudge ſhall give mee at that day: And not to mee onely, but to them that love his appearance.</hi> And to that end our bleſſed and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous father dayly giveth to all thoſe that are his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen ſonnes and ſervants, not onely the eye and hand of faith, whereby they both ſee and alſo apprehend the pretious promiſes of bliſſe and happineſſe made to them, but withall he giveth them the ſure Anchor of hope: by which (it being faſtned upon that migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty rocke the Lord Jeſus Chriſt) they ſtay themſelves with an aſſured expectation of the fulfilling and fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of them, either heere, or in heaven; in this life, or that to come.</p>
            <p>And for the further clearing the truth of this, I ſhal not offend (I truſt) if I ſhew unto you how neare the Heathens come to us in this poynt, by relating unto you a ſtory which I have formerly read in one of their writers; who though a Heathen,<note place="margin">Plutarch. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolat: ad Apolonium.</note> yet of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable eſteeme to this day amongſt us. The ſtory then in a word is this.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Upon a time (ſaith hee) a complaint was ſent from the Ilands of the Bleſſed, to the judges of the Superiour Courts, about certaine perſons ſent thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who formerly had lived impiouſly; humbly intreating, that this abuſe thus offered to them, might ſpeedily be redreſſed, whereupon theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertiall judges taking the buſineſſe into their ſerious
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21508:13"/>
conſiderations, found not only the complaint to be true, but withall the reaſon and cauſe thereof: which was, that judgment and ſentence was paſſed upon men heere below in their life time. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it oft fell out, that many perſons cloathed with honourable carkaſſes, riches, nobility, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like dignities and advancements, brought many witneſſes with them, who ſolemnely ſwore in their behalfe, that they deſerved to bee ſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Ilands of the Bleſſed; when the trueth was, they deſerved the contrary: to avoide which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniency, it was decreed by an eternal doome, that for time to come, no judgement ſhould bee paſſed untill after death; and that by Spirits only, who alone doe ſee and plainely perceive the ſpirits and naked ſoules of ſuch, upon whom their Sentence and Uerdict was to paſſe. That ſo of what eſtate and condition ſoever they were, they might receive according unto their workes.</q>
            </p>
            <p>By all which, it plainely appeareth how farre the Divine eye of this naturall man led him; ſurely unto the true finding out of a Divine and heavenly truth, which is, that neither definitive ſentence is to bee paſſed upon any heere below, nor that any whatſoever ſhall receive his full reward of that hee hath done, whether it bee good or bad, till after this Life.</p>
            <p>And ſo much in way of anſwer to the Objection. And now a word or two of his Life and Death.</p>
            <p>Neither muſt it be imagined, that intreating of the ſame, I intend any large Diſcourſe of him, as of one going to his grave in a full age,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 5.26</note> as a ricke of corne
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21508:13"/>
comming in due ſeaſon into the Barne (and the glaſſe of his life being fully runne,) but I muſt meaſure my ſelfe, by that ſhort life of his; a minute, a ſhaddow, yea, the dreame of a ſhaddow quite vaniſhed and gone, before one can ſcarce tell twenty. For if the holy Prophet <hi>David</hi> living the age of threeſcore yeares and ten, compareth his life unto a ſhaddow.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 108.28</note> 
               <hi>Pſalme</hi> one hundred and eight, <hi>verſe</hi> twenty eight. <hi>I am gone like a ſhaddow (ſayth he) that declineth, and am toſſed up and downe like a Graſhopper.</hi> Then ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Life of this young Gentleman, ſcarce attay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to one of the three, cannot bee ſo much as a ſhaddow, but muſt needs be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the meere dreame of a ſhaddow, of no long continuance. According to which, my purpoſe is to abreviate and ſhorten my Diſcourſe without multiplying many words, or telling you wonders and ſtrange miracles: ſhewing you rather what hee was like to have beene, then what hee was; and by a ſmall taſte, giving you to underſtand how pretious this Wine would have beene, had it by age and continuance beene through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purified and refined.</p>
            <p>Briefly then wil I ſhew unto you, his honeſt, devout, holy and Chriſtian Life, and condition, was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what above the ordinary garbe and faſhion of Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle-men of his age and quallity, which may appeare not onely by Religion truely implanted in his breaſt, but by many morrall Uertues and Uertuous morallities; like ſo many ſparkling Diamonds, ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their light abroad, and ſhining clearely in his path of Life.</p>
            <p>And firſt for his Religion, my onely deſire is,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21508:14"/>
that all may know that (which he himſelfe would by no meanes hide) that the religion he imbraced, was the <hi>Proteſtant-religion,</hi> which himſelfe ſuckt in with the milke of his Nurſe: and which moſt of his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors theſe many ages conſtantly profeſſed.</p>
            <p>And as with his mouth he confeſſed unto ſalvation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10. So with his heart he beleeved unto righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe: neither croſſing, much leſſe condemning by his contrary courſe, the bleſſed way wherein his Fathers formerly walked: but upholding rather, and continuing their honourable memory, by his owne vertuous life and converſation; as may appeare by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers inſtances, which I will rather number, then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt long upon.</p>
            <p>And firſt, his exceeding great delight that he had in thoſe holy exerciſes of Prayer, and reading of the Word, morning and evening in the family where he lived, from which hee ſeldome exempted himſelfe, except it were upon urgent occaſion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, his high eſteeme that he had, as of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate prayers, ſo of publicke, giving precedency to the ſame, before the other, as having more pretious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes annexed to them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, his Aſſiduous and dilligent reſorting to the publicke preaching of the word of God; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever wiſedome was pleaſed to open the gates of her faire beautifull Temple unto him.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, his religious and Chriſtian behaviour, when hee was preſent at the Church; not carrying of himſelfe as a ſevere cenſurer, but as a devout Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, not as though Almighty God was beholding to him (as moſt imagine) for his bodily preſence, but
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21508:14"/>
as one infinitely indebted to him for his divine and ſacred ordinance.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, his love and hearty affection to all good Chriſtians in general, as fellow heires and copartners with him in that rich inheritance.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, his reverent regard that he had of ſuch mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters as he knew to be faithfull and diligent in their places: honouring the Elder as Fathers,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.1</note> and the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger as Brethren.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, in avoyding (what he could) the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of wicked and deboiſhed perſons, or if hee were by occaſion driven amongſt them, then in the ſpeedy freeing himſelfe from them, as ſoone as conveniently he could, without giving offence or ſhew of incivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
            <p>And thus could I goe on in numbring many more; but I will ſtay a while: And the reaſon is, for that me thinkes I heare ſome of the ſpider-catching rowt, whoſe religion principally conſiſteth in ſearching the lives of thoſe in whom they ſee any eminency (above themſelves) thus ſecretly, and underhand whiſpering together.</p>
            <p>
               <q>This that hath beene ſpoken already of the vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous life of this young Gentleman, is ſomething, but no great matter: for we looked for farre greater things then thoſe, and more flouriſhing fruites of his Faith.</q> Juſt <hi>Naaman like. What no more but this, waſh in</hi> Jordan <hi>ſeven times, and be cleane? I had thought (ſaith he) he would have ſurely come out, and called on the name of his God; and have ſtroaked his hand upon the place, &amp; ſo have recovered the Leproſie,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 5. <hi>verſe</hi> 10.11. Now to anſwere ſuch as theſe,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21508:15"/>
in a word or two, as perſons not deſerving many.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it cannot be denyed by the moſt malicious detractour, but that the things before mentioned (if there were no more) doe ſufficiently manifeſt, that this Gentlemans faith was not vaine,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.26</note> nor his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion verball.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it muſt be conſidered, that circumſtances doe uſually much alter the ſtate of the queſtion, in things (otherwiſe) of the ſame nature and condition, for inſtance: A River to have the ſprings open, and the waters running with a full ſtreame, when the time of the yeare ſerveth fit, and all other ſtreams are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe full, is no great matter, nor is much regarded: but to have a River like to <hi>Nilus</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> when all other Rivers are flatteſt, then to riſe moſt, and ſwell, is a matter of great admiration; and calleth for the cleere eye of the naturaliſt to find out the true cauſe thereof. Againe, for a Tree to flouriſh in the Spring, and bee fruitfull in Summer, when all other Trees beſides have on their beſt and richeſt Robes, is not worth the mentioning: but for a tree in the dead of winter, when all other trees do fade and caſt their leaves: then to hold her colour, her ſap, and fruitfulneſſe, is a glorious ſight; and carrieth with it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a kind of wonderment and admiration. And ſo for a young Gentleman, being under the Ferula of a ſharp Tutor, or the frowne of a ſevere Father: his whole living depending upon his fathers love: for him to walke ſmoothly (and it may be religiouſly) is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable thing: and yet not greatly to bee truſted; ſeeing it may ſpring from a bitter roote, and to bee done to a ſiniſter end. But for this young gentleman,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21508:15"/>
having no Father to threaten, or Maſter to be contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; borne unto a great eſtate, and part thereof al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in his owne poſſeſſions: being in the luſt and vigour of his youth, and living in a royotous and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious Age: For him (I ſay) to walke as formerly I have ſhewed, cannot, (I trow) conſidering theſe and many other the like circumſtances, but be judged of him that hath the leaſt ſparke of charity in his breaſt, as the fruites of a religious heart, and worthily deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving higheſt praiſe.</p>
            <p>But leaving theſe, and ſo returne backe againe where firſt I met this clamorous generation, I will adde unto the former fruits of faith, foure other no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and commendable vertues.</p>
            <p>The firſt whereof was, his humble and courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous carriage, and demeanor towards all, even thoſe of the meaneſt and loweſt degree, not looking on them, as the faſhion of the Gallants of our Age is (as upon dogges) not upon men and women; of the ſame nature, fleſh and blood, reaſonable ſoules, wrought and framed after the ſame glorious Image; but whatſoever he was, he had a courtious welcome from him, the hat gently vailed, and the hand of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and love reached forth unto him: Shewing herein not onely a fruit of the Spirit <hi>Galathians</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.22. but himſelfe a right Gentleman; ſeeing that Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility or Courtiſie is <hi>Soror nobilitatis:</hi> the <hi>Siſter of Nobility:</hi> and as one of the ancients further ſpeaketh, <hi>Mater noſtrae philoſophiae;</hi> the breader and mother of Chriſtians Philoſophy, or rather true wiſedome and religion.</p>
            <p>The ſecond was his modeſty, appearing not
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21508:16"/>
only in his maidenlie countenance, but in his whole carriage and converſation an excellent vertue in him, and much to bee deſired in theſe impudent daies of ours, wherein bluſhing is helde the eſſentiall marke of a baſe and ignoble Spirit: and an whores fore-head is reputed the onely rare feature and eſpeciall grace:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.5</note> whereas St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the 4. of the <hi>Phil.</hi> 5. teacheth the <hi>Phillipians</hi> another leſſon, <hi>willing them to cloath them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as with other vertues,</hi> ſo (ſaith hee) <hi>with mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie.</hi> And an ancient Father ſaith, that modeſty is <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namentum nobilium, &amp; nobilitas ignobilium:</hi> the noble mans beauty, and the poore mans dignity. Yea, the <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> ſtate, and Common-wealth, received it as a Maxime and maine principle from <hi>Lycurgus</hi> their Law-giver, that aboue all things, they ſhould accuſtome their youth to baſhfulneſſe and modeſty. He onely by the light of nature finding, that which daily experience teacheth us: that impudency and boldneſſe in youth, is an evill ſigne, and the breeder of much vice and vanity.</p>
            <p>The third Uertue was his <hi>temperance,</hi> fit to bee joyned with the former, not onely for that modeſty and temperance (as the heathen could ſay,) <hi>in eodem choro ſunt</hi>) are companions in the ſame ranke: but for that the Apoſtle deſcribeth them as loving ſiſters, daughters of the ſame Spirit, walking hand in hand together. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. Now this <hi>temperance</hi> of his appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (as in other things) ſo likewiſe in theſe two.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in his ordinary habit &amp; attire, which although it were farre from baſeneſſe, ſo was it uſually much lower then the highth of his meanes, he rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting that <hi>indumentum fidej,</hi> the inward cloathing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21508:16"/>
of the mind, then the outward cloathing of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and himſelfe to be an ornament to his cloathes, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then his cloathes to be an ornament to him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it appeared in keeping himſelfe free from three raging ſinnes, over-flowing the bankes of Modeſty and Temperance in this age of ours, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Swearing,</hi> or blaſphemy.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Ebriety,</hi> or Drunkenneſſe.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Venery,</hi> or uncleanneſſe.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In regard of all which three, his innocent and ſpotleſſe life, was ſuch, as the blackeſt tongue can no way ſoyle or blemiſh his bleſſed memory. Yea, let it bee written in Cedar tables, or in golden letters upon his Tombe or Hearſe, to his eternall and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall prayſe, that when theſe ſinnes moſt raged, then was not hee with them, the leaſt way touched; but like a bleſſed River, kept himſelfe in his pure ſtreame, from beeing infected with this brackiſh and over-flowing Ocean, which to too many are over-whelmed in, in theſe our ſinfull dayes, and perilous times.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt Uertue of his (wherewith I will bound my diſcourſe this way) was his liberall and bountifull diſpoſition, witneſſed both by many charitable actions of his, to divers whom hee knew ſtood in need of his preſent helpe: as alſo by many worthy and cheereful promiſes of his future helpe &amp; favour, both to his tenants, and alſo his pooreſt neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. The conſideration whereof, together with his hopeful life begun, &amp; ſo untimely ended, cauſeth this
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21508:17"/>
generall ſorrow which wee ſee in all, eſpecially in thoſe formerly mentioned: it beeing a received opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion (as well it might) that through the Almighties helpe, he would ſuddainly have rayſed agayne the name and honour of his ancient Family: not ſuffering his Fathers houſe to ſtand, (as moſt of our Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens houſes do now a dayes) like a paynted <hi>Mercury</hi> in the way, to tell the Travailer whoſe formerly it was: Or elſe like a wracke upon the <hi>Sea,</hi> to diſcover onely where that noble Lady <hi>Hoſpitality</hi> fatally pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed.</p>
            <p>And this ſhall ſerue to bee ſpoken of the firſt act of his Life: I wil now come to the ſecond, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſpeake a word or two of his Death (the which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing briefly done) I wil then draw the Curtayn, and ſo conclude this ſorrowful <hi>Sceane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the very entrance whereof, me-thinkes I find a wonderful correſpondency and agreement, betwixt his, and the death of other of his next and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble friends: as for example,
<list>
                  <item>1. His Death was paynefull, and ſomewhat contagious, occaſioned by the ſmall poxe, a diſeaſe fatall to that Family.</item>
                  <item>2. His death was ſuddain, &amp; very dolorous.</item>
                  <item>3. His Death was ful of Piety, and excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Religious.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>1. In the firſt, you have the Death of his grand father, and grand-mother.</item>
                  <item>2. In the ſecond the death of his Father.</item>
                  <item>3. And in the laſt, the death of all three: or if you will, the death of the Righteous.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:21508:17"/>So that a man may ſafely ſay, of his Life and death, compared with theirs, as that holy King <hi>David</hi> long ſince ſpake of <hi>Sauls</hi> and <hi>Ionathans</hi> (the Father and the ſonne) 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1</note> 
               <hi>They were lovely and pleaſant in their lives, and in their deaths they were not divided.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leaving this, and looking yet more narrowly into his Chriſtian end: wee cannot (if wee doe but hearken to the credible report of thoſe who were continually with him, from the beginning of his ſickneſſe, to the delivering up of his laſt breath,) but take ſpecial notice amongſt many other, of theſe two things right commendable in him:
<list>
                  <item>1. His admirable patience.</item>
                  <item>2. His true and hearty repentance.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The one, in induring; the other in deſiring: the one in performing; the other in promiſing.</p>
            <p>And firſt for his Patience, it was ſuch, that conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the tenderneſſe of his Age, the frailty of Youth, and want of experience in ſickneſſe, that (as it is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally reported) it was a matter of great admiration to all about him. For however our heavenly Father gave way (as it ſeemeth) to the diſeaſe to fanne and winnow him, as Corne is fann'd and winnowed to the utter-moſt: yet did he in the meane while ſo ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and ſtay him with the hand of his Mercy, that neyther his hope loſt her hold, or his faith failed. So that howſoever the outward man ſuffered, yet the inward man was renewed daily. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16</note> How ever his body was not his owne, being under the hand of a ſharpe Chyrurgion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 21.1</note> yet in patience he did poſſeſſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21508:18"/>
his ſoule: of all which hee gave ſufficient teſtimony, both by his milde and ſweete behaviour; as alſo by his comfortable words, and Chriſtian language. For here were no impatient ſpeeches, no murmurring and repining, no crying out upon the diſeaſe: no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing of ſecondary cauſes, but a patient ſilence, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted, now and then, with ſhort prayers, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ejaculations: wherein he craved at the hands of God, eyther mitigation of his payne, or ſupply of ſtrength, eyther to be eaſed, or graciouſly to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported.</p>
            <p>And heere wee have an Embleme or a patterne of true Magnanimity appearing plainely in this, that when the ſtormes of temptation and trouble raged moſt, and theſe ſharpe cutting winds blew lowdeſt; yet hee carryed himſelfe, ſo cloſe under the ſhield of Faith, that hee was not at all daunted, or driven from that obedience which hee did owe to God; or his duty towards his neighbour. The which, as it is a noble and excellent vertue and quality of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; ſo was it (queſtionleſſe and without doubt) much holpen:
<list>
                  <item>1. By the true ſight hee had of ſinne.</item>
                  <item>2. By the true ſence and feeling of the Love of God towards him.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt for ſinne, if a man doe but ſeriouſly (as I doubt not, but this Gentleman did) weigh and ponder in his heart, both the number of his ſinnes (being indeede without number) as alſo the nature of them, not onely croſſing, but alſo, violating the pure Law of an infinite God, and ſo deſerving an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21508:18"/>
puniſhment: hee ſurely cannot but with a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and contented mind beare and indure theſe ſhort and light afflictions: how ever bitter for a time, yet bringing with them in the end, the ſweete fruites of righteouſneſſe: Crying with the Church, <hi>Micah</hi> 7.9.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.9</note> 
               <hi>I will beare the indignation of the Lord, becauſe</hi> I <hi>have ſinned againſt him.</hi> And <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.22.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.22</note> 
               <hi>It is the Lords mercy that</hi> I <hi>am not conſumed.</hi> And agayne, <hi>Patior do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine quia peccavi, &amp; patior ut non peccarem:</hi> (as a holy man ſpeaketh) I know ſweete God, that I ſuffer for that I have ſinned. And agayne, I know that I ſuffer, that I might not ſinne. Theſe are the files, whereby thou doeſt labour to ſcowre my heart, and cleanſe me from my ſinnes: and this is the Gall and Worme-wood wherewith thou doeſt ſtrive to weane me from the pleaſant pappes of this world, and make me wholy diſtaſte the pleaſure of this wicked and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full life.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, the ſence and feeling of the love of God, which queſtionleſſe, had a mayne and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall ſtroake in putting this Gentle-man on (as hee did) to drinke ſo willingly of this bitter cup. For, as ſoone as ever the love of God doth but once dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, and ſhed it ſelfe abroad into the hearts of any his faithfull ſervants, then preſently ſuch abundance of heavenly ſtrength, and vigor, joy, and comfort doth enter with it, that hee feeleth not at all the burthen of affliction; or if hee doe, hee findeth it very light. Hee feareth not the fiery tryall, for well hee knoweth, that though the hardeſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth; yet will it in the end worke out for his good, as a Fatherly correction, no finall deſtruction:
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21508:19"/>
yea, triumphing in a glorious manner, hee ſaith to Death: <hi>Where is thy ſting; or what haſt thou to ſeparate me from the love of God?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15 <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.35 <hi>Ioh</hi> 5.22</note> 
               <hi>For as for deſtruction, I laugh at it, neither doe I feare the Beaſt of the field. Iob.</hi> 5.22. And hence is it, that <hi>Daniel</hi> was ſo coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and bold for the ſervice of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.10</note> that he durſt open his window at the time of prayer, though the denne was open to ſwallow him, and the hungry Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ready to devoure him.</p>
            <p>Hence againe was it, that the three children with ſuch magnanimity and ſpirit ſo ſlighted the Tyrants ungodly command, ſaying as they did. <hi>Dan</hi> 3 16. <hi>Wee are not carefull to anſwere thee in this matter, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe wee care what thou canſt doe unto us: For our God whom wee ſerve is able to deliver us, and hee will deliver us out of thine hand:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.16</note> 
               <hi>But how ever aſſure thy ſelfe ô King, wee will not ſerve thy gods, nor wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip thy golden Image which thou haſt ſet up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, hence was it, that thoſe moſt noble con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors <hi>Dionyſia</hi> and <hi>Victorianus</hi> ſo conſtantly, and with ſuch an undaunted courage, indured thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull torments and ſcorching flames of Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. The one crying out, <hi>De Deo ſum ſecura, cruciate ut libet.</hi> I am ſure of Chriſt, a fig for your torments. The other, <hi>ſecurus ſum de Chriſto Domino me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>haec dicite regi veſtro, &amp;c. I am reſolved of the love of Chriſt my Lord and my God: and therefore tell your King from me, that I weigh not his torments a ruſh.</hi> If then the love of God was ſo ſtrong in theſe, no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile then, that this young Gentleman feeling the ſame in his tender heart, ſo patiently and with ſuch contented mind, paſſed through not onely the bitter
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21508:19"/>
               <hi>Symptomes</hi> of his cruell malady, but alſo through the ſhadow of death it ſelfe: For Love (ſaith the Church, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.6, 7. ſpeaking by her owne experience) is ſo ſtrong, that death it ſelfe cannot quell it, nor all the water in the Ocean quite drowne it.</p>
            <p>But leaving this, let us come to the ſecond, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, his true and hearty repentance.</p>
            <p>For the cleere demonſtration whereof, it muſt bee conſidered how the Spirit of God in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, mentioning true repentance, doth commonly uſe two words in themſelves very ſignificant and full of divine expreſſion.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The firſt whereof ſignifieth an after wit.</p>
            <p>The other an after ſorrow.</p>
            <p>By the one, underſtanding a poore penitent loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king backe upon his former courſe of life, and then finding how he hath beene guld by Sathan, deluded by the World, and beguiled by the deceitfulneſſe of his owne heart; he cryeth out <hi>Heu miſer! quot mala feci? Alas wretch that I am! What evill have I done?</hi> and thereupon looketh for time to come more narrowly to himſelfe.</p>
            <p>By the other ſetting forth a ſorrowfull crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſtriking on his thigh, grievouſly vexed for his ſinnes paſt, asking pardon, and promiſing a new life.</p>
            <p>In the firſt of theſe we have <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iame.</hi> 3.17</note> That wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from above. <hi>Iames</hi> 3.17.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond we have <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that ſorrow to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God; and in both together (mixed with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21508:20"/>
faith) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that repentance never to be repented of,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10</note> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10.</p>
            <p>An example of both theſe meeting together in one, wee have in this young Gentleman, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare plainly by the circumſtances following.</p>
            <p>The firſt was his ſpeedy and timely caſting off the world upon the firſt arreſt of his ſickneſſe, together with the vaine pleaſures and delights thereof; ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by his practiſe unto her, as that Heathen <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher</hi> ſpake unto his rich treaſure, when hee was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to caſt it into the Sea: <hi>Abite a me peſsimae volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates, ego vos mergam, ne mergar a vobis. Away from me ye bewitching pleaſures, I will drown you, that you drowne not mee:</hi> or rather as they are fore-told to ſpeake to their Idols,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.22</note> throwing them away with a kinde of deteſtation. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.22. <hi>Apage cui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp;c. Away, get you hence fawning world. Thou pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Iezabel, and flattering Harlot, now doe I ſee the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of thee in Chriſt is exceeding eaſie; my bleſſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter telleth me that he hath already overcome thee:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh</hi> 16.33</note> 
               <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling me to be of good cheere, and ſo I am: My ſoule mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying the Lord, and greatly rejoycing in God my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, being fully reſolved that I at the laſt in him ſhall obtaine the like noble victory over thee, that this young Gentleman hath done before me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond was, the exact ſurveigh that he tooke of his former life, wherein however (bleſſed bee God) he found not thoſe <hi>Damnabilia peccata,</hi> as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> calleth them, from which (ſaith the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father) youthfull age is ſeldome free; yet thoſe that hee found (although they were but aberrations onely, and no impieties, <hi>delicta non facinora:</hi> weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21508:20"/>
and infirmities; no flagicious offences; yet was he much troubled at the ſight of them; oft crying out with righteous <hi>Iob: Paenitet me:</hi> and with that holy Prophet <hi>David Pſal.</hi> 45.7. <hi>peccatum pueritiae mea ne recorderis Domine. Lord remember not the ſinnes of my youth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obſerve next his carefull providing of his Via<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum or things neceſſary for his departure; his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring and fitting of his Lampe with oyle, and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent expecting of the <hi>Bridgroomes</hi> call.</p>
            <p>In all which (as is the generall report) his care was more then ordinary: neither was there any one thing in Heaven or Earth, which he ſo much deſired, as he did that full aſſurance of his reconciliation with God, &amp; to underſtand what that love of Chriſt was, that paſſeth all underſtanding; not that hee doubted at all thereof, for he found the beginnings and fruits of the ſame (as formerly I have ſhewed) already in his ſoule, mightily cheering up, and comforting thereof: onely he deſired yet more, that hee might at the length be filled with the fulneſſe of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 7.19.</note> 
               <hi>Eph.</hi> 7.19. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> like the little infant that having but once taſted of the milke of the mother, is never contented, but mourneth, and cryeth until it be fully ſatisfied, and the belly filled therewith: or like the hunted Stagge in Summer-time, who finding a pleaſant ſtreame, having once taſted of it, is never ſatisfied untill hee hath ſounded the bottome, and duckt himſelfe overhead and eares therein: or rather like that faire Bride, (the Church I meane) <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.6.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.6.</note> who thinketh her ſelfe never ſure of her ſpouſe and love, untill his <hi>Left hand bee under her
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21508:21"/>
head, and his right hand doth imbrace her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Life hee ſimply deſired not, and death hee ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhly feared not, for he knew right well that which came firſt, ſhould bee his gayne and great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. And becauſe for want of ſleepe, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant, and fiery working of his Diſeaſe, hee fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red much, leaſt any diſorderly, impatient, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ſpeeches ſhould paſſe from him, to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Almighty God, and griefe, and ſorrow of his Friends about him: His requeſt therefore was hourely to God, for Chriſts ſake, to ſet a watch before his mouth, and to keep the doore of his lips. And if at any time it hapned (as ſeldome it did) that his braine beeing ſomewhat over-heated, he a little ſwarved from the right rule, and ſo forgot himſelfe: his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was, after the violence of the fit was over, (upon inquire made, and the truth thereof found) humbly to beg pardon for the ſame, &amp; with teares to bewaile it.</p>
            <p>All the time of this ſharpe tryall, and viſitation of his, was, for the moſt part, daily ſpent, eyther in holy conference with ſuch graue Divines as were continually about him for his ſoules health, or in hearty prayers preſented before the throne of grace, and powred into the golden Cenſure of the ſonne of God; wherein earneſt requeſt was made unto the Father, that though this young ſouldier of his, were thus ſtrongly aſſaulted, yet that hee might ſo keepe himſelfe upon the legs of his Faith, that hee might neyther be foyled,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 23.10</note> nor yet led into temptation, and that though hee were tryed unto the full, yet that hee might in the end come out like pure Gold. <hi>Iob</hi> 23.10. Neyther did this bleſſed ſervant of God, hold it
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21508:21"/>
ſufficient to have others pray for him, except he like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe performed the ſame duty himſelfe; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring well, that hee that hath but once drunke a full draught of the River of Grace, it cannot be,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.38</note> but out of his belly muſt needes flow rivers of water of Life.</p>
            <p>The which prayers of his, were delivered with ſuch contrition of heart, ſuch Faith reſting it ſelfe upon the promiſes of God, ſuch patient and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſubmiſſion of himſelfe to the will of his gracious Father: that it was an admiration to all about him, to behold ſo tender a plant to bring foorth ſuch delicate and precious fruite. And thus while his body is here below, his ſoule is ſeeking after things above: his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy a priſoner laden with gyves and fetters of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, his ſoule is at liberty, ſoaring up on high, and ſweetly converſing with that bleſſed ſociety in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly places. The which it did divers dayes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther going and comming, till at laſt (like another <hi>Noahs Dove</hi>) it quite left his troubled <hi>Arke,</hi> and this tempeſtuous World, mounting up a loft above all earthly things, and ſeated it ſelfe uppon the pleaſant Mount <hi>Syon, Vbi moritur omnis neceſſitas: Vbi oritur ſumma faelicitas:</hi> where all want ceaſeth; and all bliſſe increaſeth: even that place where are thoſe fragrant and delightful fields, repleniſhed with all the trees of Myrrhe, Frankincenſe, and Alloes, with ſweete beds full of the richeſt and chiefeſt ſpices,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.12, 13.</note> where he dayly feedeth, and ſo ſhall doe till that bleſſed day breake, and all ſhadowes flye away.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant</hi> 4.6</note> And thus have I as brie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly as I could, without either wringing or churning (be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing loath to lye for him, as a man lyeth for his friend,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 30.33</note> 
               <hi>Iob</hi> 13.9.) ſet forth to you, the Life and Death of this
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21508:22"/>
young Gentleman. The which the more I thinke of, the more I cannot but highly commend that true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Wedlocke, and mirrour of widow-hood, the noble and vertuous Lady (his ſorrowfull mother) for her religious and Chriſtian educating of him, all his young and tender yeares; dropping then grace into his heart, and filling the ſame with Heavenly liquor, the pleaſant ſcent thereof, never left him unto the laſt houre and minute of his life.</p>
            <p>Her extraordinary care this way, I ſhall not neede at large to relate unto you, ſith the whole Country round about, can ſufficiently witneſſe the ſame, to her immortall praiſe; onely this I will ſay, that if the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture (as wee know it doth) maketh ſuch ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable mention of <hi>Berſheba,</hi> and <hi>Evnice</hi> for their diligence in teaching their Sonnes, <hi>Solomon</hi> and <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,</hi> in their tender age, the trade of their way. And againe if holy <hi>Auguſtine</hi> aſcribeth to his mother <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acha</hi> her teares and prayers (next under God) the ground of all the good, that after ſo many wandrings and wanton actions of his, at length appeared in him. And laſtly, if <hi>Cornelia</hi> be ſo highly remembred in the <hi>Roman</hi> ſtory, for bringing up thoſe famous <hi>Gracchi</hi> her ſonnes ſo carefully as ſhe did in their infancy and growing yeares, making her the mother not onely of their naturall lives, but alſo of their vertuous living, and Heroicke demeanour: I cannot ſee why his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Lady ſhould not have the like honour, and high reſpect at the hands of all, for the religious care over this her ſonne, from his birth to his laſt breath. And therefore being ſo, however Almighty God, for cauſes beſt knowne to himſelfe hath thus (as we ſee)
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21508:22"/>
taken away the ſubject of her deſired and chiefeſt care, not ſuffering her lippes ſcarce to taſt the fruite of that which ſhe with a deale of paines had ſo many yeares together carefully ſowne: yet may ſhe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in comfort her ſelfe, that neither was her labour ſpent upon a barren or unfruitfull ſoyle, neither is her bleſſed ſonne loſt, whom Heaven hath found, but is there, whether wee are daily travailing; reſting himſelfe under the tree of life, and ſatisfying his ſoule with endleſſe pleaſure: To which moſt ſacred place, the Lord in his good time for his Chriſts ſake bring us all, Amen.</p>
            <p>And thus have I at the length finiſhed the firſt part, of this my intended diſcourſe, wherein (I muſt needs confeſſe) the unfained love I did alwaies beare to this noble plant, hath, I know not how, put words into my mouth, and thruſt me on to a unwilling tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Leaving him therefore in the armes of Chriſt, I wil now with what ſpeed I can proceed to the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of that portion of Scripture: whereof (by Gods gratious aſſiſtance) I minde to treate of, the latter part of the time allotted me.</p>
            <p>And this you ſhall finde written <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.19. The words are theſe.</p>
            <q>Thy dead men ſhall live: even with my body ſhall they riſe. Awake, and ſing, yee that dwell in duſt:<note place="margin">The text.</note> for thy dewe is as the dewe of Hearbes, and the earth ſhall caſt out the dead.</q>
            <p>FOr the more orderly handling of which words, my purpoſe is to obſerve this order.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:21508:23"/>Firſt, to ſpeake ſomething of the Chapter in generall.</p>
            <p>Secondly, having once cleered the Text, to take it in peeces, and to ſpeak of every perticular part by it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Now, in ſpeaking of the Chapter in generall, I will,</p>
            <p>Firſt, briefly touch the manner, that the prophet uſeth in indighting of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſpeake a word or two of the matter or ſubject thereof.</p>
            <p>And firſt for the manner: it is not the ſame with moſt of the former Chapters; but is expreſſed and ſet downe in a differing ſtile, they in proſe and this in verſe: For in all the former Chapters (ſave onely the firſt) wee finde (as hee that hath the leaſt skill in the Text knoweth) the holy Prophet delivering his matter in proſe; however, full of divine trops, and heavenly expreſſions. And in this Chapter toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the firſt, wee finde him ſo poſſeſſed, and rapt up with the unſpeakable love of God toward his Church, that hee thinketh the higheſt ſtraine low enough to expreſſe the ſame. And therefore delivereth his minde, not after his wonted manner in plainneſſe of ſpeech, but in a high and ſtately verſe: that ſo divine conſolations might come like the ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <hi>Nectar,</hi> carried along in Golden pipes to the hearts of his hearers: For things delivered in verſe,</p>
            <p>Firſt, worke better on the fantaſie, then ſuch as are delivered in proſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, come neetlier, and more richly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21508:23"/>
apparrelled unto the underſtanding.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, take a great deale ſurer hold upon the memory.</p>
            <p>And therefore the bleſſed ſervants of God, and holy Prophets and Propheteſſes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.1 <hi>&amp;c. Iudges.</hi> 5.1 <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.1</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid; Debora</hi> and <hi>Anna, &amp;c.</hi> when they would preach and ſet forth to the World thoſe <hi>Magnalia Dei,</hi> thoſe wonderfull deliverances and favours of GOD to his Church: that they might take the deeper impreſſion in the hearts of all, expreſſed them in ſacred Verſe, whence queſtionleſſe, thoſe <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bills</hi> likewiſe: and thoſe ancient Law-givers in el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der dayes, borrowed their mould, and patterne in penning their Lawes, and propheticall conjectures in Verſe, not in Proſe. The greater ſhame therfore it is, for many in theſe dayes of ours, to abuſe that divine gift as they doe: fitting <hi>Davids</hi> Harpe to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fidling tune: and abuſing the Bowles of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to the ſervice of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> and drinking healths to <hi>Abaddon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leaving the manner, let us come unto the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or ſubject, of this heavenly ſong, from the 1. verſe to the end of the 19. In all which is contained much variety, and matter of great diſcourſe: For there wee have to mention ſome two or three things, amongſt others very remarkeable.</p>
            <p>Firſt, a diſcription of the true Church of God: namely:
<list>
                  <item>1. A City full of power.</item>
                  <item>2. Citizens full of piety.</item>
                  <item>3. City, and Citizens, full of all felicity.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:21508:24"/>Secondly, wee have ſpirituall boaſtings.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Of the faith of the children of God.</item>
               <item>2. Of the holy uſe that they made of their afflictions above wicked and prophane worldlings.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Laſtly, a ſpirituall cordiall, or rather unſpeakable comfort, afforded to all the true children and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God, that the Lord will when time ſeemeth fitteſt, deliver not onely them, but theirs, not from light afflictions, but from the greateſt: yea the whole <hi>Iſrael</hi> of GOD out of all his tribulations.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 25.22</note>
            </p>
            <p>And this latter, is that which the Prophet princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally delivereth in this 19. Verſe (which I have read unto you): The true meaning whereof, that we may finde out the better; it muſt bee remembred that the Children of God; members of the true Church, apprehending by the eye of faith, that great tryall and ſore affliction, namely the <hi>Babilonian Captivity,</hi> ſo univerſally proclaymed, by all the holy Prophets of the Lord now approaching, and neare at hand, were at this time in great dolour and perplexity of minde: And blame them not; for what one outward triall can be imagined, of a more cutting and corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiving nature, to the heart of man, then Captivity is? fith by the meanes thereof; a man is uſually at once deprived of all his joy; and of a free-man turned to be a ſlave: Thoſe <hi>dulcia arva</hi> and native ſoile, where firſt hee tooke his breath, hee ſeeth no more: and if hee doth, it is with an heavy heart; yea, Riches, Wealth, Honour, together with religion (dearer then his life) are ſtraight-way loſt, whilſt hee himſelfe like the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21508:24"/>
baſeſt abject, imbraceth the feete of the proud and diſdainefull conquerour. The horrid ſight whereof, putteth the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> into ſuch a bitter paſſion, that he cryeth out, as you may ſee, <hi>Ier.</hi> 14.22.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 14.22</note> 
               <hi>Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cera mea: Viſcera doleo, &amp;c. My Bowels, my Bowels: I am pained at the very heart, I cannot hold my peace, becauſe thou haſt heard ô my ſoule the ſound of the Trumpet, and alarum of Warre.</hi> And our Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> likewiſe, as may appeare by thoſe his words <hi>Chap</hi> 22.4. <hi>Looke away from mee I beſeech you, for I will weepe bitterly, labour not to comfort mee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.4</note> 
               <hi>becauſe of the ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling of the daughter of my people.</hi> If then ſuch mighty and valiant Captaines as theſe, beganne at the ſight thereof to quake and tremble; what ſhall we then ſay of the common Souldiers? certainely, their feare muſt needs be <hi>Panical,</hi> and they exceeding affrighted.</p>
            <p>To help and cure which, it pleaſed Almighty God, not onely to inſpire the breaſt of this ſanctified and holy Prophet of his, with the cleere light and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of his diterminate Counſel, and decree here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: but alſo to fill his pen with ſweet and comfortable predictions, all tending this way; that this great affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and tryall of theirs, ſhould onely bee but for a time, and that after the ſpace of 70 yeares, they ſhould ſhake off the yoak of captivity and bondage from off their ſhoulders; now for that this was a thing hard to be beleeved, and altogether impoſſible in their weak conceits, as may appeare by their words. Behold,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.11.</note> (ſay they) <hi>Our bones are dry, our hope is gone &amp; we are cleane cut off:</hi> we find not only the Prophet <hi>Ezekel</hi> in the forenamed chapter; but our Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> in the verſe that I have read, labouring from God to ſettle &amp;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21508:25"/>
ſtabliſh their wavering and doubtfull hearts in the truth thereof, both by a ſtrange viſion, as alſo by an invincible argument taken from the <hi>Reſurrection of the dead.</hi> The which, as it is a mayne principle in true Chriſtian Religion, beeing an <hi>Article</hi> of our <hi>Faith,</hi> a Maxime in <hi>Divinity,</hi> imbraced of all the whole Society of Gods faithfull ſervants; ſo beeing certaynly beleeved, and by the arme of <hi>Faith</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, as an infallible and undoubted truth, it will ſo ſtrengthen and cheere up the heart of him that is the ſervant of God, that hee ſhall neyther feare the moſt fierce and fiery tryals: nor yet queſtion any of the promiſes of <hi>Almighty God,</hi> how difficult, &amp; even impoſſible ſoever they appeare to a carnall eye.</p>
            <p>For inſtance: whence was it that <hi>Abraham,</hi> that bleſſed <hi>Patriarcke,</hi> with ſuch conſtant Reſolution ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, that in time hee ſhould imbrace a ſonne, how ever the courſe of nature cryed loud againſt it:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.17</note> was it not (as it is playne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.17.) for that hee that promiſed, was <hi>Hee that raiſed the dead, and calleth things that are not, as though they were!</hi> Whence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne was it, that holy <hi>Iob,</hi> that meeke and humble ſervant of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> with ſuch admired patience indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſtripping of all his goods; the loſſe of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and the remooving of his hope from him like a Tree: was it not (as hee himſelfe acknowledgeth, <hi>Chapter</hi> 19.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 19.15.26.</note> 
               <hi>verſe</hi> 15.26.) For that hee was reſolved that his <hi>Redeemer lived, and that at the latter day, hee ſhould ſee God in his fleſh?</hi> Whence, (laſtly) was it, that <hi>Moſes</hi> eſteemed the reproach of Chriſt, grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then all the treaſures of <hi>Aegypt:</hi> was it not the fight hee had.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11</note> 
               <hi>Hebrewes</hi> the eleventh <hi>Chapter:</hi> of him
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21508:25"/>
that was <hi>Inviſsible, and aſſured hope of the recompence of reward, after this life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No marvaile then, that our Prophet (as I ſaid) laboured to ſettle the minds of this dejected people, with an argument taken from the ſame: It being full of comfort, as alſo forcible to perſwade; drawne (as you ſee) <hi>a maiore ad minus,</hi> from the greater to the leſſe: The nature of which, that we may finde out the better, wee will in this verſe conſider theſe two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Conſolation.</item>
               <item>2. A Reaſon.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, the Conſolation, is no other then a joyfull concluſion, taken and drawne (as formerly was ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) from the reſurrection of the dead; in theſe words: <hi>Thy dead men ſhall live, even with my body ſhall they ariſe: awake and ſing yee inhabitants of the duſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon is laid downe in way of Fortification, or ſtrengthning of the conſolation, in theſe words. <hi>For thy dewe is as the dewe of hearbes, and the earth ſhall give up her dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Conſolation we finde,
<list>
                  <item>1. That there is a reſurrection of the dead.</item>
                  <item>2. The manner of the ſame.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In ſpeaking of the firſt, wee will obſerve two things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The truth of this Article; that there is a Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:21508:26"/>2. The quality of the perſons that are ſayd to ariſe, in theſe words: <hi>Thy dead men ſhall live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the manner of the Reſurrection, we find it,
<list>
                  <item>1. Very beautifull.</item>
                  <item>2. Very Joyfull.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt in theſe words, <hi>With my body ſhall they ariſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond, ſet foorth by a kinde of <hi>Rethoricall</hi> paſſage or <hi>Apoſtrophe,</hi> or turning of his ſpeech to the Dead, willing them to <hi>awake and ſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the reaſon is no other then a forceable argument taken and drawne from the vertue and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the Reſurrection of Chriſt, which in the end wilbe the ſame to the dead, that the Dew is to the hearbes, filling and inforcing the earth to caſt up her dead.</p>
            <p>Of all theſe things in order, and very briefly.</p>
            <p>And firſt of the conſolation in generall: that there is a <hi>Reſurrection of the dead,</hi> in theſe words: <hi>Thy dead men ſhall live, &amp;c.</hi> The which as it is a comfortable propoſition, ſo it is delivered by him, not (as <hi>Tully</hi> delivered his concluſions of the contempt of Death) faintly and doubtfully, but with great confidence &amp; fulneſſe of aſſurance. <hi>And</hi> iuſtly, whether wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the univerſallity of this truth, it being conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imbraced of the whole Church of God, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all ages: but likewiſe the antiquity of the ſame, it beeing infolded in that firſt, and gracious promiſe made to <hi>Adam</hi> our Father in aſſuring him, <hi>Gene.</hi> 3.15.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21508:26"/>
               <hi>That the ſeede of the woman ſhould breake the Serpents head.</hi> And hence it was, that <hi>Heva</hi> the Mother of us,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15</note> and all the living, having brought forth <hi>Seth,</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth (as ſhe doth) <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.25.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.25</note> 
               <q>Repoſuit mihi Deus Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men alterum, &amp;c. Oh <hi>(ſaith ſhe)</hi> God hath given me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <hi>Abel:</hi> He hath kept him for a time, and now at length hath reſtored him to me againe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The like divine conſolation, poſſeſſed (queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe) the beleeving heart, not onely of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but of all the holy <hi>Patriarches</hi> beſides, as may appeare both by their ſervent and longing deſire after the <hi>Meſsiah,</hi> whom they knew, was ordained by the Father to be the Reſurrection and the life: as alſo, by the honourable teſtimony, that the Author of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> giveth of their faith herein. <hi>Cap.</hi> 11.13.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13.</note> when he ſaith that <hi>They all dyed in the Faith, not having the promiſes, but having ſeene them a farre off, and were perſwaded of them, and imbraced them; and confeſſed that they were ſtrangers and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimes on the earth,</hi> And therefore (ſaith hee) <hi>verſe</hi> 16. <hi>God is not aſhamed to be called their God: for he hath prepared for them a City.</hi> This was likewiſe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable doctrine,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod,</hi> 3.6</note> which Chriſt our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our preached in the buſh to <hi>Moſes Exod</hi> 3.6, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe averreth. <hi>Mat</hi> 22.31.32.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.31, 32.</note> when he thus ſpake un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. <hi>I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Iſaac, and the God of Iacob.</hi> This was that which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in all his writings publiſhed, affirming withall, both before the governour <hi>Faelix,</hi> and that honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable aſſembly. <hi>Act.</hi> 24.15.16.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 24.15, 16</note> That it was a maine principle which put him on to have a pure conſcience towards God, and towards men, and to account (as
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21508:27"/>
he telleth the <hi>Phillippians Chap.</hi> 3.7, 8.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.7.8</note>) thoſe things that were advantage to him, but as loſſes, ſo that hee might attaine the reſurrection of the dead.</p>
            <p>Yea, the holy Scriptures are not onely plentifull in Teſtimonies proving the truth thereof; but in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples likewiſe, of perſons dead, and ſome of them rotting in their graves, who have by the power of Almighty God beene perfectly reſtored to life again; my labour therfore in further proving the truth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, may (I doubt not) be the better ſpared; eſpecially conſidering it is an Article of our faith, univerſally received, of the whole Church of God, at all times and ages:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deu.</hi> 29.18</note> notwithſtanding, if there be any here, in whoſe wicked heart, there is yet the root of Gall and Wormewood; ſo that when hee heareth this, hee bleſſeth himſelfe in his froward and wicked courſe, as though there were no ſuch reſurrection, or further reckoning to bee expected. Let ſuch a one (if the booke of God will not give him ſatisfaction) looke abroad into the large volumne of Nature, where que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſſe (if his eye bee not too much dimmed with the fog and miſt of Athiſme and prophaines) he ſhall be ſure to finde the infinite wiſedome and power of Almighty God, in ordering and diſpoſing by the hand of providence many other things, (not unlike in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but altogether is impoſſible to the judgement of man as this is) to their ſeverall ends, which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his eternall decree at the firſt he had determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. For inſtance: there ſhall he finde the glorious Lampe of the World, (the Sunne I meane) in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening going downe, having his beautifull eye clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the ſhaddow of the night; and himſelfe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21508:27"/>
quite covered over, with the thicke and black mantle of the ſame, as with his winding ſheete; and ſhrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in darkeneſſe, continuing for a time, untill his <hi>Creator</hi> mindfull of his covenant (the morning ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching) raiſeth him up againe in ſuch a glorious manner, that loe he commeth forth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.15.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.15</note> 
               <hi>Like a Bridgroome out of his chamber, and reioyceth like a ſtrong man to runne a race.</hi> There likewiſe ſhall he ſee the Moone waſting and wayning away, untill at length ſhee ſeemeth quite loſt and gone; but within a few dayes after, he ſhall ſee her againe, filling her hornes with light, and the Heavens with brightneſſe: There ſhall hee behold the infant buried certaine moneths in the wombe of his Mother; but in the end, comming forth upon the ſtage of the World a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Creature,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 15</note> and richly adorned with the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the Creator. There laſtly ſhall hee ſee, the Corne not quickned except it dye, nor the trees and plants of the earth flouriſhing, untill firſt they have endured a Winters death. But if neither the Booke of God, nor yet of Nature, can give ſuch a cavelling, and Athieſticall wretch as this is ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; I for mine owne part ſhall give him over to the ſeate of Juſtice, to bee anſwered as they were, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 13.2. rather <hi>verbere quam verbo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 13.2</note> with the fiſt of the Magiſtrate; then with any diſpute or force of argument. And ſo I come to the perſons that ſhall ariſe in theſe words.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:21508:28"/>
Thy dead men ſhall live.</q>
            <p>FOr the further cleering of which words two que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions muſt of neceſſity be anſwered.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, whether theſe words doe not croſſe thoſe in the 14 <hi>ver.</hi> before going? For there it is ſaid, <hi>Thy dead men ſhall not live:</hi> And here it is ſaid, <hi>That they ſhall live:</hi> and that <hi>They ſhall ariſe:</hi> Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>live</hi> and <hi>not live, not riſe,</hi> and <hi>ariſe,</hi> a man would thinke were a plaine contradiction.</p>
            <p>The ſecond queſtion, is, why the Spirit of God termeth them, the Prophets dead men, and not dead men in generall, in theſe words.</p>
            <q>Thy dead men ſhall live.</q>
            <p>To anſwere both in order. Firſt we are to know, that there is no contradiction, no ſaying, nor unſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, betweene the words of my Text, and thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly delivered in the 14. verſe: For whereas our Prophet ſaith in the 14 verſe. <hi>Thy dead men ſhall live:</hi> or as ſome will have it: <hi>They are dead, ſhal they not live, &amp;c?</hi> or as others, <hi>Hi mortuj non vivent, ſuch dead men as theſe ſhall not live.</hi> He poynteth out que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſſe wicked and ungodly perſons formely men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in this Chapter: Such as our Saviour Chriſt aimeth at,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.22</note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 8 22. when hee willeth that offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Diſciple to ſuffer, <hi>The dead to bury their dead.</hi> And on the other ſide by the word <hi>(Thy)</hi> (a plaine note of difference and diſtinction in theſe words of my Text) our Prophet doubtleſſe notes out a ſpecial, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21508:28"/>
choſen company differing from the reſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.6</note> over whom death hath no power: but they ſhall live eternally. In a word.</p>
            <p>Firſt by thoſe in the 14 verſe: <hi>Not living: Not ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing!</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.21</note> our Prophet underſtandeth perſons dying in their ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, thoſe in my Text: <hi>Living</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13</note> hee underſtandeth perſons dying in the Lord.</p>
            <p>And verily wicked men dying in their ſinnes, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are partakers of the firſt Reſurrection; neither doth their Reſurrection, deſerve at all ſo honourable a denomination: For as the Death of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, cannot properly be ſaid to bee a death: it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as one ſaith wel) <hi>Occaſio vitae, non deletio:</hi> a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther living, not an utter quenching of the Lampe thereof: ſo on the other ſide, the reſurrection of the wicked cannot (as I have ſaid) properly be called a Reſurrection, it being a meere precipitation; and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting headlong of an unbeleeving catiffe, into the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring jawes of the ſecond death, and fatall gulfe of eternall deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Both in deed, good and bad, him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not, ſhall be raiſed up at the latter day: and yet their reſurrection ſhall much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. Whether we conſider,
<list>
                  <item>1. Either the manner of the Reſurrection.</item>
                  <item>2. The end of the ſame.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt for the manner.</p>
            <p>The Childe of God is raiſed up by the hand of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21508:29"/>
mercy, the wicked man and reprobate, by the hand of Juſtice: the one by the vertue of the death and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, piercing into his grave; even as you ſee the Sun and ſhowers in the ſpring, ſweetly ſoaking and ſinking downe into the roote of the plant, cauſing in it immediately to bud and bloſſome forth. The other, by the arme and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Almighty God, who ſhall then judge both the quicke and the dead; and who ſhall quoit him out of his grave, like a raging and horrible tempeſt that caſteth up both ſtones and dirt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the one ariſeth like a miſerable Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive in the fetters of the ſecond death: the other, like a Free-man, in the garments of Glory: the one commeth forth like a condemned perſon, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the wrath of God like a cruell Goaler, han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging on his arme, and hayling him from his grave, as from a ſtinking Dungeon, unto the place of execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: the other, commeth forth like a Bridgroome richly apparelled, to meete his beloved ſpouſe: or like a baniſhed man who is now arrived upon his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſoile.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as they differ in the manner, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe doe they differ in the end of their reſurrection: the one to bee graciouſly rewarded, the other to bee grievouſly tormented: the one to receive the reward of the righteous, the other to receive the doome of the wicked: the one to be received into their Maſters joy, the other to bee clapt up in the priſon of woe: the one, laſtly, to make good that dreadfull ſentence paſſed upon <hi>Adam, Geneſis</hi> 2.17. <hi>In the day that thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17</note>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:21508:29"/>
               <hi>dye the death.</hi> The other to fulfill that bleſſed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made by Chriſt to the faithfull,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11.15</note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leventh, <hi>verſe</hi> fifteenth: <hi>I am the Reſurrection and the life.</hi> For till then, wee ſhall not cleerely ſee the fruite, either of that undoing ſinne of <hi>Adam,</hi> or of that eternall ſacrifice, which Chriſt (the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous) preſented to the Father, when hee was pleaſed (in his infinite mercy) to dye for our ſinnes, and riſe againe for our juſtification: then it plainely appeares,</p>
            <p>Firſt, what the ſecond death meaneth, and who they are, that are truely curſed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, what eternall life is, and who they are that are truely bleſſed.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, what Chriſt did for us, and that he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not in vaine, where with theſe eyes of ours, we ſhall ſee millions cloathed with glory and immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and of poore men made rich, of beggers, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>By all which, it is moſt cleere and evident, that godleſſe perſons (ſonnes of <hi>Belial</hi>) have no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at all to looke for the Reſurrection day, but with <hi>Faelix, Acts</hi> twenty foure, <hi>verſe</hi> the ſecond,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 24.2</note> to tremble at it, ſith to them it will bee a day of Darkneſſe, and not light: yea, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry darkneſſe, and no brightneſſe in it. For however they ſhall eſcape the pound of the Grave: yet the ſecond death, ſhall like a cruell Wolfe, eagerly purſue them, overtake them, and quite maſter them; ſo that their freedome from death, ſhall bee no other benefit to them, then if a man fled from a Lyon, and a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21508:30"/>
Beare met him: or entring the houſe, and leaning his hand on the Wall, and a Serpent bit him. To the children of God (onely) it wil bee a joyfull day: their marriage day: a day of great ſolemnity: A day wherein their redemption draweth neere? A day wherein their vild bodies ſhal be made like the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous body of the Sonne of God (as wee ſhall ſee after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward more plainely.)</p>
            <p>The ſecond queſtion is, why the ſpirit of God cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth theſe dead men, the Prophets dead men, in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Thy dead men ſhall live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwere diverſly: As firſt, for that theſe perſons formerly were his proper and peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar charge, and he ſet over them, not onely as a watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to informe them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eze.</hi> 3.17 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.11 <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.5 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 21.15</note> but a ſhepheard to feed them: And therefore his people, his flocke: for ſeverall congregations, are ſo many Miniſters flockes: and all the ſoules therein their ſpeciall charge: to them they are in truſt committed: and at their hands one day they will be certainely required.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eze.</hi> 3.18.19, <hi>&amp;</hi> 33.8</note>
            </p>
            <p>Hence was it, that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in his farewell Sermon, ſo earneſtly exhorteth the Elders of <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 26.28</note> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 26.28. to feede the flocke of Chriſt. <hi>Over which</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Holy Ghoſt hath made you over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> all miniſters in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.13. aſſuring them withall, that in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, <hi>When the great ſhepheard doth appeare, they ſhall receive a Crowne of Glory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.13</note> that fadeth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they are ſaid to be his dead, for that he was formerly a principal inſtrument, and meanes, for the converſion of their ſoules; freedome from
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21508:30"/>
their naturall bondage;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 26.18 <hi>Rom</hi> 8.22</note> and bringing of them into that bleſſed liberty of the ſonnes of God. So that now they are his dead, who formerly obtained life by his helpe: For this is an high priviledge and prerogative which onely belongeth to the Miniſters of the Word, lawfully called; as was <hi>Aaron,</hi> not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be the Embaſſadors of the ſonne of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cor</hi> 3.9.</note> but his fellow-workers alſo: yea Saviours (inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally) of the ſoules of men: the which doth plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare, not onely by that wee read in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of <hi>Obadiah ver.</hi> 21. where he fore-telleth;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obad.</hi> v. 21</note> 
               <hi>That in the latter dayes Saviours ſhall come up upon Mount Syon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tim.</hi> 14.16</note> But by the exhortation that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> giveth his beloved <hi>Timothy:</hi> willing him to have a <hi>care both to himſelfe, and to his doctrine: for in doing ſo,</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>thou ſhalt ſave thy ſelfe, and thoſe that heare thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The conſideration whereof, ought not onely to be as pretious Wine, warming of our breaſts, but a ſpurre and goad in our ſides, that are the Miniſters of the Word, putting us on cheerefully to paſſe through the miery waies of ſcorne and contempt, which we dayly meete withall, as wee walke along, carefully performing the duties of our calling: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring,</p>
            <p>Firſt, though it bee heere in this World a calling much contemned, yet is it in heaven highly honoured.</p>
            <p>Secondly, though it bee a calling full of paines, yet it bringeth in the end unſpeakable comfort.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore, not ſo much eye the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21508:31"/>
as the wages: the preſent worke, as the future reward.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, they are ſaid to be his dead, for that he had not yet given up a perfect account for them. And no marvaile, for the Audit day was not yet come, when both hee and his people muſt appeare face to face before that glorious Tribunall, of that dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Judge; who with an unpartiall eare, will heare all things paſſed betwixt them, and give ſentence accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly: For death ſealeth not a Miniſter his <hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> neither is he fully diſcharged of his flocke and cure, untill that day, wherein the Sonne of God holding his general Aſſizes, ſhall require at his hands, a particular account, both for himſelfe, and alſo for all thoſe, who were formerly his flocke and people. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.19.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The due conſideration whereof, made the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles, to preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell with that aſſiduity and diligence as they did.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.28</note> 
               <hi>For that</hi> (ſaith he, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.28.) <hi>our deſire is to preſent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man perfect in Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> which being ſo, firſt of all, happy and bleſſed is that man, whom when his Maſter commeth, ſhall finde ſo doing: yea, happy and bleſſed is that miniſter,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk</hi> 12.36</note> and painefull labourer in the Lord, who having worne out his Age and ſtrength in the ſervice of the Church, and like a pretious lampe conſumed himſelfe to give light to others, is now laid up in peace, in the midſt of a number of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and familiar acquaintance, it may bee, by his meanes, brought to the true knowledge and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding both of God and themſelves: what a bleſſed ſight wil it be, when that day is come, and that dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21508:31"/>
voyce, <hi>Surgite mortui,</hi> ſhall ſhake Heaven and earth, to behold both him, and al thoſe ancient friends of his, lively leaping out of their graves, clothed all in pure robes, ſhining and gliſtering as the light. Oh who can expreſſe the joy that wil be then, at this their meeting againe.</p>
            <p>But above all, the joyfulleſt ſight will be, to behold that welcome which the Son of God will then give him, with that <hi>Enge ſerve bone &amp; fidelis: Wel done good ſervant and faithfull:</hi> When hee upon his bended knee, and al his company kneeling round about him, ſhall then ſpeake unto him, ſitting upon his glorious Tribunall. <q>Thou Almighty King and ſupreame iudge of the whole World. Loe here I am, and the children that thou haſt given unto me.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa</hi> 8.18</note>
               </q> The which doubtleſſe will be a ſight ſo full of joy, that my tongue is not able to expreſſe the ſame: my deſire onely is, that into that or the like aſſembly, my ſelfe may one day come.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as the eſtate of the faithfull labourer wil then be happy, ſo on the other ſide,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11.16, 17</note> the condition of him that is an unfaithfull labourer, will queſtionleſſe prove moſt miſerable.</p>
            <p>How carefull the Elders were in former times o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſoules of ſuch as were committed to their charge, may appeare by one example, which may ſerve in ſtead of many: of St. <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Clemens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>drinus &amp; Sozo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menus.</note> the bleſſed Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, (ſtanding upon record in Eccleſiaſticall ſtories) which I will as briefly as I can relate unto you.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Iohn</hi> (ſaith the ſtory) after the death of the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant (meaning as I take it <hi>Domitian</hi>) returning out of the Ile of <hi>Pathmos,</hi> and comming to the City of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> where having ordayned Elders, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatched
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21508:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
much other buſines co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the Chrcuh, he commeth at length to a certaine City not farre of, whoſe name (ſaith the Author) many at this day doe well remember, where amongſt divers others there aſſembled, he eſpyed a certaine young man, migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in body, and of a beautifull and manly counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: whom after he had earneſtly beheld, the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Apoſtle turning himſelfe to the Biſhop of the place, after this manner ſpake unto him: <hi>I doe heere</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>in the preſence of Chriſt and his Church, commit this man unto thee to be trained up, and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with thy greateſt diligence.</hi> And ſo immediately after, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> returned againe to <hi>Epheſus.</hi> The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop receiving the young man thus committed to his charge, tooke him home with him, and through his extraordinary care ſo wrought upon him, that within a ſhort time, hee was thought fit, not onely to bee Baptized, but to have a certaine cure, in the Lords behalfe committed to him. But after this, the young man having obtained his former liberty, fel into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany againe, of certaine of his olde ompanions, Idle and diſſolute perſons, that firſt drew him to their ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otous feaſts and banquets; and after that to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrating and committing of far greater miſchiefes and wickedneſſe: So that now he is not onely an aſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate of thoſe wretches his companions, in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of many Murthers, Robberies, and other hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible out-rages: but by reaſon of the excellency of his wit, manlineſſe of heart, and ſtoutneſſe of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, he is made their head and Captaine. In the meane time, <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> comming againe into thoſe parts, and meeting by the way with the Biſhop
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21508:32"/>
before ſpecified, required of him the pledge which (ſaid hee) in the preſence of Chriſt and his Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, I left in thy hands to keepe: The Biſhop ſomewhat amazed, ſuppoſing hee had ſome money committed to his cuſtody, which he had not as yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, knew not what anſwer he ſhould make unto him. The which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> perceiving: <hi>The young man,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and ſoule of our brother, committed to your cuſtody, is the pledge that I require:</hi> The Biſhop underſtanding his meaning, with teares running downe his cheekes, thus replyed. <hi>He is dead</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>dead unto God, being now become a moſt wicked perſon, a companion of theeves and villaines, and haunting theſe mountaines and deſarts hard by.</hi> At the hearing whereof, the bleſſed Apoſtle rending his Garments, with great lamentation, ſaid unto him: <hi>I have left a good keeper of my brothers ſoule.</hi> And thereupon deſiring inſtantly a horſe and a guide, rod directly to the place where this damned crue haun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, where being preſently taken by ſome of that company, hee earneſtly requeſted of them to bee brought unto their Captaine: who comming to him armed as he was, at the firſt beganne to look fiercely on him; but immediately comming to the knowledge who hee was, as a man wholy confounded, began to flye and run from him. But the old man follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him as faſt as he might, forgetting his age, and crying, <hi>My Sonne, why doſt thou flye from thy Father? an armed man, from one without weapon? a young man from an old man? Have pitty on mee my ſonne, and feare not, for there is yet hope of ſalvation: I will make an anſwere for thee unto Chriſt: I will dye for
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21508:33"/>
thee (if neede be) as Chriſt hath dyed. I will give my life for thee. Beleeve mee Chriſt hath ſent mee.</hi> The yong man as one amazed, firſt ſtood ſtill, and then caſting downe his weapons, trembling, and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly weeeping, imbraced the old man, being bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized afreſh againe, through aboundance of teares running downe his manly cheekes: whom after the Apoſtle had upon his knees fervently prayed for, he brought back unto the Congregation; to which, after ſome time of humiliation and dayly faſtings, he was happily at length reſtored.</p>
            <p>The ſtory is too long for me to comment upon: let him that hath an eare harken what venerable antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſpeaketh:</p>
            <p>I come now to the ſecond thing to be conſidered in my Text, namely the manner of their reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: the which is deſcribed by the bleſſed Spirit; as we heard to be:
<list>
                  <item>1. Very Beautifull.</item>
                  <item>2. Exceeding joyfull.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt, beautifull, in theſe words:
<q>With my body ſhall they ariſe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The which ſtanding (as they doe) in the originall, carrie with them a doubtfull conſtruction, which maketh Interpreters ſomwhat to vary in their tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations: For that which ſome tranſlate, <hi>With my dead body ſhall they ariſe:</hi> others turne, <hi>My dead bodies, or my dead body ſhall ariſe.</hi> The matter is not great in in which ſence the words bee taken, ſince they are
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:21508:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſo neere a kinne, and carry with them ſeverall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions, full of Divine truth and ſweete conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, then, if we take the word as the ordinary tranſlation hath them, and read them thus, <hi>With my dead body ſhall they ariſe:</hi> Then muſt we take the Son of God in the ſame, comforting of his Church, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the ſeverall members thereof, with an aſſured hope of a moſt glorious reſurrection. So that however, the brutiſh and ungodly as hee fell,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 24.21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</note> ſo hee ſhall ariſe, and having his bones full of the ſinnes of his youth which (<hi>Iob</hi> 20.11.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 20.11.</note>) lay downe with him in the duſt) ſhall come forth under the Tyranicall command of the ſecond death, the reſurrection of condemnation: yet the ſervant of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2</note> the true ſonne of the reſurrection, <hi>Iohn</hi> the fift,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.2</note> 
               <hi>verſe</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: However his body was ſowne in weakneſſe, yet ſhall it riſe againe in power, and putting off the rotten ragges and patched mantle of corruption,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor</hi> 15.47</note> ſhal be richly cloathed and apparelled with the pure and pretious garments of ſalvation:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.7</note> In affirming therefore that thoſe dead bodies ſhall ariſe with his glorious body, he intimateth thus much: That when that day of refreſhing ſhal come from the preſence of the <hi>Lord:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aact.</hi> 3.19</note> he who is the reſurrection and the life, ſhal not onely remove all deformity of nature, but worke a bleſſde conformity betweene himſelfe who is the head,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.49.</note> and all ſuch as are ſeveral members of his bleſſed body, that as they have borne the Image of the earthly; ſo ſhal they then beare the Image of the heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Then ſin, together with the fruits &amp; woeful effects thereof ſhal wholly ceaſe; and howſoever the bodily
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21508:34"/>
ſubſtance ſhal remain, yet the qualities therof, ſhal be wholly changed. So that for ſickneſſe there ſhal be health: for deformity beauty: for baſeneſſe glory, for lumpiſhneſſe agility: yea, for weakneſſe ſuch aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of ſtrength;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach</hi> 12 2</note> that hee that is feebleſt amongſt them, ſhall be as <hi>David, and the houſe of David, as Gods, and as the Angell of the Lord before them.</hi> For as by death our naturall infirmities are fully cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.3</note> ſo in the reſurrection (every way ſo glorious) our former loſſes ſhall perfectly be reſtored, whilſt we all come unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of Chriſt. By meanes thereof;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.4 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.5, 6 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.9</note> we ſhall not onely obtaine a freedome from all miſery, but a fruition of all good. Thoſe things that wee doe now weakly beleeve, we ſhall fully imbrace. And thoſe glorious things dayly ſpoken of thee, thou rich inheritance of the Saints of God, we ſhall both ſee and taſte. For inſtance, then we ſhall by joyfull experience finde:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The greatneſſe of the Sonne of God, his purchaſe, and infiniteneſſe of his love: that he that knew no ſinne, ſhould be made ſinne for us, that wee might be made (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21) <hi>The righteouſneſſe of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. What thoſe robes are of Chriſts righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and how pretious thoſe Garments are of our Elder Brother; which the bleſſed Apoſtle ſo much deſired.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.5 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.4</note> 
               <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.5. together with the miſery and moſt unhappy condition of thoſe that want them 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.4.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What the Crowne of Immortality and Life meaneth: and whether it bee worth the blood of ſo many Martyrs and holy Confeſſors as have beene
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21508:34"/>
ſpilt from righteous <hi>Abel</hi> until now, for the obtaining of it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, what a glorified body is, and the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and excellency of the ſame; when our bodies ſhall be light and nimble, paſſing up and downe, as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wings of the Winde: when our dayly foode ſhall be the love of God; and all our drinke drawne out of the River of Celeſtiall pleaſures; when our bodies ſhall be tranſparent like the pureſt Chriſtall: and our ſoules ſhining through the ſame, like ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſparkling Diamonds: when God laſtly ſhall bee all in all, the vaile remooved, and wee for ever with him.</p>
            <p>The which in themſelves, are things ſo excellent, that whilſt I am ſpeaking of them; me thinkes I heare my ſoule thus ſecretly complaining: <hi>Heu mihi peregrinor tandin, &amp;c. Alas that I ſoiourne in</hi> Meſech,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120.5 <hi>Rev.</hi> 22</note> 
               <hi>and dwell ſo long in the Tents of</hi> Kedar. <hi>Lord Ieſus come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, if we take the words as ſome tranſlate them: <hi>Cadavera mea reſurgent: My dead Carcaſſes ſhall ariſe:</hi> then queſtionleſſe (in calling them his dead carkaſſes) the bleſſed ſpirit aſſureth them, of his ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall care over them, untill the day and time of their reſurrection commeth: ſo that although they have left the world, yet are they not quite loſt, but when they are not, then are they his dead Carkaſſes. A dead Carkaſſe, though of the deareſt friend, wee ſee uſually, few will owne. A memorable exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (amongſt many others) wee have in <hi>William</hi> the ſecond the <hi>Conquerors</hi> ſucceſſor, who being fatally kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and now falne to the earth: all his company,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21508:35"/>
Nobles, and others, inſtantly forſooke him, ſave only a few of the meaneſt ſort, who laying his Princely Corpes uppon a homely beere, drew it into a houſe or lodge neare at hand; now if this were the portion of ſo mighty a Prince, whom immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before, ſo glorious a troop, ſo royally attended: what muſt others then of meaner ranke expect and and looke for, but onely with deaths cloſing up their eyes, to have all their friends excluded, and no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner gone, but to be as ſuddainely forgotten. For O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blivion and neglect,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87.8</note> are the two handmaids of death, and her Kingdome where ſhee principally tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth is <hi>Terra oblivionis,</hi> The land of forgetfulneſſe: when as <hi>David</hi> therefore would expreſſe the worlds ingratitude, in the higheſt degree toward him; he fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth her compariſon from her uſuall manner in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting of the dead.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.12</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.12. <hi>I am forgotten</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>like a dead man out of minde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And from this evill faſhion, grew that ancient and uſuall cuſtome of erecting monument over the dead, <hi>ut ment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m moneant, ad defuncti memoria,</hi> that they might retaine and keepe in memory perſons formerly departed: the conſideration whereof, as it cannot queſtionleſſe, but much trouble the dying heart, even of the deareſt ſervant of Chriſt (who na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally is ſociable and deſiring the company of man) as we ſee in <hi>Ezechias</hi> dolefull complaint <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.11.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.11</note> 
               <hi>I ſhall ſee man no more with the inhabitants of the earth:</hi> So ought the very hearing that all the dead bodies of the Elect, are the Sonnes of God, his dead carkaſſes, and peculiar charge, mightily to cheere up their dejected ſoules, at the laſt houre and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21508:35"/>
period of their lives. If then it happeneth (as oft it doth) that theſe or the like Melancholly thoughts (uppon the approach of Death) enter thy troubled breaſt, and thus thou ſecretly muſeſt with thy ſelfe. <hi>I ſee mine houre and time is now at hand, when I muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and ſuddainly make my bed in darkneſſe, in the ſlimey valley; whither my friends will not care to come, and mine acquaintance tremble to approach: where my onely Comrade muſt bee corruption, and the worme my chiefe companion.</hi> Then remember, that being Chriſts in thy lifetime, thou art his when thou art dead; then his living <hi>Temple,</hi> and now his dead carkaſſe. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth his love at all fayle, when breath fayleth: For however others perhaps will loath thee: yet bee ſure hee will not leave thee; but cloſing thy dying eyes with his gracious hand; will go along with thee unto thy Grave, where having ſowne thee like pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſeed, will not forſake thee until hee ſhall rayſe thee in a moſt glorious manner. For even as thoſe infernal ſpirits are never abſent from the Graves and tombes of Reprobates, prophaine and wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; but there they are tryumphing over them, as their ſpoyle and conqueſt: ſo is the ſonne of God never abſent (by his Divine preſence) from the Graves and monuments of all pious and Religious perſons, perfuming them with the odoriferous ſavour of his death and paſſion; and ſo preſerving of them, that not a bone of them is loſt. The which being ſo,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34 20.</note> when that time commeth, and dye I muſt, <hi>egredere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nima mea, egredere,</hi> go forth my ſoule, go forth, feare not, ſo are up to that <hi>bleſſed ſociety that is above,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12:22.23.24</note> 
               <hi>that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of angels, &amp; ſpirits of iuſt &amp; perfect men; &amp; to Ieſus
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21508:36"/>
mediator, and to the bloud of ſprinkling, that ſpeaketh better things then the bloud of Abel.</hi> As for my dead carkaſe, I deliver it wholly over into the hands of my bleſſed Saviour;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12</note> being well aſſured, that he is of powerable to keep that which is thus committed to him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as the reſurrection of the elect (as I have ſhewed you) will be very beautifull, ſo againe will it be very joyfull; as may appeare by the words fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, wherein they are willed <hi>To awake and ſing.</hi> The which words may be underſtood, either.</p>
            <p>Firſt, as a rethoricall paſſage, wherein the bleſſed Spirit turneth his ſpeech to the dead bodies, willing them to <hi>Awake and ſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or ſecondly, in way of Propheſie, wherein he fore-telleth, as an addition to their future happineſſe, that they ſhall <hi>Awake and ſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then we take the words in the firſt ſenſe, then have we no other then an application, or uſe, that the ſpirit of God maketh of that comfortable Doctrine formerly declared, concerning the reſurrection of the dead, in ſpeaking to them as perſons living, and willing them to <hi>Awake and ſing:</hi> many the like paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages we meete withall in the booke of God, where we finde the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaking to things unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, as though they were reaſonable; ſenceleſſe; as having underſtanding;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.21 <hi>Deut.</hi> 30 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.1 <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.3. <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.12</note> dead, as living: ſometimes calling them forth to bee Judges: ſometimes to bee witneſſes, ſomtimes to rejoyce, ſomtimes to mourne; ſomtimes to looke boldly, ſomtimes to bluſh and be aſhamed. All which together, with the reaſon why the bleſſed Spirit cloatheth his diſcourſes in ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toricall
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21508:36"/>
and rich attire, I doe willingly omit: fearing leſt through teadiouſneſſe I might bee trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome.</p>
            <p>And yet before I wholly leave this poynt, and come unto the ſecond, I thinke it not amiſſe to touch one neceſſarie dutie, which the methode that the holy Ghoſt here obſerveth, affoordeth to us, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king (as I ſaid) ſo excellent an uſe of thoſe comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble doctrines formerly delivered.</p>
            <p>For whereas in the words preceding, he aſſureth the bodies of Saints <hi>Inhabiting in the duſt,</hi> that they ſhall not onely a riſe, but in a moſt glorious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; and that till then, they are under the wings and protection of a moſt gratious keeper: ſo in theſe words, he turneh himſelfe unto them, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this bleſſed uſe of all, willing them, <hi>To awake and ſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The which neceſſary duty, as it rightly concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the miniſters of the word, in delivering divine truth (as if time would ſerve me I might eaſily prove) ſo likewiſe doth it the ſoule of every Chriſtian, man, or woman, whenſoever they heare promiſes or threatnings publiſhed or delivered. The which that they may the better doe, a neceſſary thing it is (for feare of making falſe conſtructions) to harken what the Conſcience, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the ſoule ſpeaketh: For beeing the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding part of the underſtanding, it will eaſily tell a man how his caſe ſtandeth, either by accuſing or excuſing, abſolving or condemning. For inſtance, thou art a wicked and ungodly liver; and thou heareſt theſe, or the like dreadfull judgements,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21508:37"/>
threatned &amp; thundred out againſt Adulterers, Swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, impious and ungodly livers: <hi>That a flying booke of Curſes ſhall enter into the houſes of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 5.3.4 <hi>Iob.</hi> 15.12 15. <hi>Iob.</hi> 20.7</note> 
               <hi>and overthrow them quite. That their ſtrength ſhall bee famine, and that Brimſtone ſhall bee ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered upon their Habitations. That they ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh like their owne Dunge. And that they that have knowne them before, ſhall ſay, where are they?</hi> Now; art thou deſirous to know, whether this bee the portion of thy cup or no? then harken to thy conſcience, and marke well her words, for que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſſe upon the hearing of the ſame, ſhee will thus conclude.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 10.3 <hi>Math.</hi> 7.6</note> But thou art ſuch a one; debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched perſon, and one of this rout, and brutiſh crue; a ſtinking Goat, a filthy Swine, a ſnarling Dog: and therefore,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.2</note> all thoſe heavy judgements, and woefull plagues, are due to thee, as thy lot and portion.</p>
            <p>One the other ſide, thou art one, upon whoſe heart the Word of God hath wrought effectually; ſo that now thou wholly ſeekeſt after things above. Thine Eye, thy Tongue, thy Hand, thy Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimes Weedes; namely, Mortification and a new Life doe plainly ſhew it: Many promiſes thou dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meeteſt withall, like delitious Waters, drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping out of the Bucket of <hi>Iacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.1 <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.10</note> the which thou art exceeding deſirous to know whether they bee thine or no? A thing that thou maiſt eaſily doe, if thou wilt but liſten what thy conſcience ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, which upon the hearing of the ſame, will aſſuredly after this ſort, both aſſume and reply: <hi>But thou my deare friend, my yoake-fellow and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21508:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
companion, art one of this bleſſed company, (as not onely my ſelfe, but my whole life and converſation doe plainely witneſſe) therefore theſe promiſes doe belong to thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, if wee take the words, in the future tenſe, in way of prediction and propheſies (as well wee may, for that in the <hi>Hebrewe</hi> language, the Imparative mood and future tenſe are ſet and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, the one uſually for the other) then have we a ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne preſervative againſt the feare and ſadneſſe of death, in that the ſpirit of God aſſureth theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the duſt, that they ſhall <hi>Awake and ſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The which, that we may the better ſee, we are to conſider:</p>
            <p>Firſt, who the perſons are, whom he termeth, <hi>Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the duſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, their happy eſtate and condition at the latter day, in that they ſhal <hi>Awake and ſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt, the perſons, that are termed here the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitant of the duſt,</hi> we are to underſtand no other then thoſe formerly mentioned under the name of his dead: variety of expreſſion ſetting forth the ſelfe ſame perſons, as may appeare not onely by the word <hi>(Yee)</hi> as putting a ſpeciall difference betweene them and others; but alſo, for that though that all, good &amp; bad, ſhal awake and riſe, yet all not awake &amp; ſing:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.13</note> but the greateſt company ſhall (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 65 13) <hi>Cry for ſorrow of heart, and howle for vexation of minde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> But why are they called the <hi>Inhabitants of the duſt?</hi> why doth not the bleſſed Spirit give them a more noble denomination? not rather Gods
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:21508:38"/>
               <hi>Iewels?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Proſ.</hi> 13.14 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.10</note> Gods <hi>Redeemed? Hoſ.</hi> 13.14. Gods <hi>choſen. Eſay</hi> 35.10. or as formerly hee did, his dead car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſſes, but inhabitants of the duſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I anſwer.</hi> Firſt, generally to declare and manifeſt the mutability of all humane fleſh: and that there is nothing in man, or in the ſonne of Man, whether Riches, Honour, Beauty, ſtrength, or wit, yea pure Religion, (farre more precious then them all) that can hold him whom death will have, or latch the arrow that death ſhooteth. This is that <hi>David</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.48</note> when he thus ſpeaketh, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 89.48. <hi>What man is he that liveth, and ſhall not ſee Death? ſhall he deliver his ſoule from the power of the grave?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, and more particularly, the reaſon is three fold.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.17.</note>Firſt, for that it was the eternall decree and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Almighty God; appoynted to man upon his fall, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.17, that hee ſhould once dye, and after Death, ſhould come to judgement.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for that the whole ſeede of <hi>Adam,</hi> hath Death mixed with it; yea, the tender infant ſucketh and draweth it in, with the milke of the mother.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, for that man hath a certaine inclination to Death, as the flower hath to fade, or the tree to fall.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in a more particular, and ſpeciall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, they are called the inhabitants of the duſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to teach every man, that to be an inhabitant of the Duſt, is an honourable thing, when, namely, the dead corpes of Man or Woman, lyeth not as dung upon the earth, but obtayneth a comely, a decent, and Chriſtian buriall. A bleſſing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:21508:38"/>
to <hi>Ezechiah, Ioſiah,</hi> and other the like no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Princes: and the contrary againe threatned as a ſore judgement agaynſt wicked and godleſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>Iezabel, Zedechiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.17 <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.4</note> and other of the like ſowre Leaven: and therefore to take it as a ſpeciall favour of God, to have not onely ours, but the bodies of our Friends to bee layd up decently in their Graves, <hi>velut precioſa, &amp; Deo chara</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as choyce gifts, deare and precious unto God; <hi>Where duſt may return to duſt, as the ſpirit formerly did to God, that gave it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to admoniſh all, but principally the great Men, and Princes of the earth, not to looke too much (with proud <hi>Haman</hi>) uppon the glory of their Riches, their trayne and followers, their honors, and high promotions, their greatneſſe, and ſwelling ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles; which if they doe, will ſo flaſh and gliſter in their eyes, that they ſhall forget themſelves, as alſo the liberall hand from whence all theſe things did come. But rather turning their backes uppon thoſe inchanting gleames and lights, let them with a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious looke daily view their original and birth, being of the baſeſt Element: their fleſh and blood common with the meaneſt ſervant: their honourable carkaſſes wearing away to their firſt Element: where all their pompe muſt leave them, and they inhabite the ſad and duſty valley.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to be a caveat to us, how wee ſcorne our poore brethren partakers with us of the ſame hope, and of the ſame houſhold of Faith;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10</note> for that their houſes are farre meaner then ours, and their cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and attire much baſer:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.10</note> For as wee are come all of one <hi>blood, the poore and the Rich,</hi> the Lord &amp; the ſlave;
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:21508:39"/>
ſo are we travailing to the ſame Land, where (there is no remedy) but we muſt dwell together, and where our houſes will not greatly differ: the out-ſide of the Rich mans, uſually much gayer, but the inſide of the poore mans, perhaps much ſweeter. There it is no diſgrace for the Princes Pallace to be neere the Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants Cottage; or the lodging of the poore beggar, to be neere unto the Miſers chamber, where the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der againſt Cottages and Inmates is of no value; ſith new Cottages are there hourely erected, &amp; hundreds dwell on heapes in baſe and ſilly Manſions: when then thy heart doth begin to ſwel in pride and with the ſcornefull thoughts, thou haſt in regard of thy brothers poore eſtate; then remember that it wil not be long ere thou and he ſhalbe both alike, and of the two, he (it may be) acknowledged by Divine ſentence the better man. Remember <hi>Dives</hi> and <hi>Lazarus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, wee are to conſider the ſeverall things, that they are fore-told to do; and theſe are</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Awake.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Sing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt, they ſhall awake; but not of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or their owne power: but by the dreadful voyce, and Almighty breath of God, willing them and us to Riſe up from the dead,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom</hi> 14.12</note> and to give a ſtrict account of what we in all our life time have done: (of which I intend not to ſpeak:) this onely we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that Death is nothing elſe, but a meere ſleepe, out of which wee ſhalbee one day awakened: thus are all the bleſſed Patriarckes, and holy Prophets, and Confeſſors,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.18.</note> dying in eldertimes ſayd (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.18.) to ſleepe. And the ſame Apoſtle writing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> uſeth this as an argument to
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:21508:39"/>
diſſwade them from over much ſorowing, as perſons out of hope for them that were departed;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.13</note> for that they did but ſleepe: yea, holy <hi>Stephen,</hi> though his death were violent; yet ſaith the Spirit of <hi>God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 7.60.</note> ſoule and body were no ſoner parted, but he <hi>fel a ſleepe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The which, (although it bee a truth) yet wee muſt not fondly imagine:</p>
            <p>Firſt death properly to be aſleepe: or,</p>
            <p>Secondly, when the bodie is dead, that the ſoule ſleepeth.</p>
            <p>For firſt of all, death cannot properly bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe; ſeeing they two are ſo quite contrary; the one a friend to man, the other a mortall foe: the one naturall, the other accidentall: the one a preſerver of life, the other a deſtroyer of the ſame. Death therefore is called uſually by the name of ſleepe; in regard onely of a kinde of ſimilitude and proportion that is betwixt them.</p>
            <p>For inſtance:</p>
            <p>Firſt, when a man is falne aſleepe, all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward labour and buſineſſe is laid aſide; hee thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not of them, neither doth hee at all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire them. So is it, when a man is dead, hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth no more the worke and labour of his hands, in all that Pilgrimage of his, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly paſſed. Hee knoweth not what hee hath done: and if you tell him, hee will not regard. Friend or foe are all one to him:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 14.21</note> neither doth he care, whether his ſonnes be honourable, or of low degree.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when ſleepe poſſeſſeth a man, paine and paſſion, feare and griefe, doth not ſo moleſt
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:21508:40"/>
and trouble him, as when he is awake. Such is the eſtate of man when once dead. Is he a priſoner? <hi>He feareth not</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iob) the voyce of the oppreſſor:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 13<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 18</note> or is he a ſlave? hee is inſtantly freed from his cruell maſter. All the threatnings in the World cannot make him quake, neither is he moved at all with the angry looke of the cruell Tyrant.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, when a man is once a ſleepe, then all his ſences are retired into their proper places, and all the members of his body ceaſe from working: not onely reſting (as formerly I ſaid) from thoſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward labours of his calling, but even from working the workes of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.28</note> Even ſo it is with him, who is once dead; his eye is no more lifted up to Heaven, as to the fountaine head of life and goodneſſe: his knee bendeth it ſelfe no more at the throne of grace; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth his tongue any more here below ſet forth the praiſes of that glorious God. Set the bleſſed trumpet of the Word to his eare, and hee heareth it not; neither is there in him any ability, or will to performe the leaſt religious duty. For the living, they are they that praiſe the Lord: the grave doth not:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.18, 19.</note> neither doe they that goe downe into the Pit celebrate his truth. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.18, 19. And therefore it being ſo, good it were for us, to follow that which our bleſſed Saviour alwaies practiced, namely, whilſt it is to day, to worke the workes of our heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn,</hi> 19.4</note> ſeeing the night commeth faſt upon us, when no man can worke.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, as the riſing of the Morning Sunne uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally expelleth the naturall ſleepe, and lumpiſhneſſe of the night: ſo at the appearing of the Sunne of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:21508:40"/>
Righteouſneſſe; the brightneſſe of his comming ſhal expell, and chaſe away the ſleepe of death, and put an end to that drowſie night, neyther ſhall we ſleepe any more the ſleepe thereof.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.3</note>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe and many other the like reſpects, is Death uſually ſtiled by the name of <hi>ſleepe:</hi> and this bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo:</p>
            <p>Firſt, why ſhould wee tremble at it, ſeeing it is the ſame to the childe of God, that the coole ſhade is, to the weary travailer;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 14.2.</note> and the evening reſt to the painefull Labourer.</p>
            <p>Secondly, why doe wee ſo bitterly weepe and mourne (as perſons without hope) for our Friends departed; for they doe but ſleepe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4 13</note> and one day aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly they ſhalbe awaked?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, why doe wee not make more account of Church-yards, and places of buriall, then wee ſee, uſually is done; ſeeing that they are the <hi>Dormito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> and ſleeping places of the bodies of the Saints; where reſting for a time, they ſhall at length bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waked againe by the comming of their Maſter, and his gracious call.</p>
            <p>Secondly, wee muſt not imagine, when the Body is dead, that the <hi>ſoule</hi> ſleepeth (an ancient, yet erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious opinion) it croſſing directly the word of God in many places: as namely, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.7. where the Preacher ſpeaking of the death and diſſolution of Man; hee thus expreſſeth it (<hi>Duſt</hi> ſayth hee) <hi>retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth unto Duſt, and the ſpirit unto God that gave it. And</hi> that of our holy and bleſſed Saviour Chriſt Ieſus to the Theefe on the Croſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.7</note> 
               <hi>Luke</hi> the twenty third, <hi>verſe</hi> forty three,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk</hi> 23.43</note> 
               <hi>To day thou ſhalt bee with
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:21508:41"/>
me in Paradiſe.</hi> This was amongſt many other of ancients, the beliefe of holy <hi>Policarpus,</hi> who (as the ſtory ſaith) when he was to enter the flaming fire in the defence of the Chriſtian Faith, openly profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that he was fully reſolved, <hi>Hodie ſeſe repreſentan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum in Spiritu, coram Domino:</hi> that <hi>he was in his ſoule that very day to appeare in the preſence of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> If it be ſo, (may one ſay) why doth then God deale ſo hardly with the body above the ſoule:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.15.</note> For are they not <hi>both the worke of his hands?</hi> The one made in ſecret, and curiouſly wrought in the loweſt, parts of the earth: and the other <hi>Creando infunditur, &amp; infundendo Creatur:</hi> like the moſt pretious oyle infuſed and powred out of the tree of Life. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides they are alwaies loving friends, ſympathizing, and taking part in the weale and woe each of other: they weepe together, and rejoyce together: why then upon their parting, goeth the one to the earth; the other to heaven? the one to a dungeon of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the other to a Pallace and place of delight?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The anſwere whereunto is, that this is done by Almighty God in ſingular wiſedome, in theſe three reſpects.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to croſſe the fond and childiſh courſe of man &amp; woman, whoſe delight wholly is as (we dayly ſee) in pampring and cheriſhing of their bodies, whilſt the care and due reſpect that they owe unto their ſoules, is wholy neglected: their bodies are deliciouſly ſtuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed; their ſoules are miſerably ſtarved: their bodies are clothed in Silke and Tiſhue; their ſoules in rags and tatters: their bodies are preſumed with the moſt odiferous oyntments; their ſoules with ſtinke of ſin,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:21508:41"/>
and blaſted with the breath of Hell.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that the body might in time be wrought and framed to be a fit companion for the ſoule, which ſince the fall of man it is not; but rather (as I have ſhewed you before) a let, and oftimes hindrance unto the ſame, in the cheerefull performance of many ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and Chriſtian duties. And therfore it pleaſed God our heavenly Father, to appoynt the earth to be his furnace and place of refyning, to waſte and weare away whatſoever ſinful contagion the body former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hath contracted; ſo that the ſoule afterward with the ſame, may no waies be incombred.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that they being thus parted,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 6</note> the ſoule might earneſtly, and hourely deſire (as the reſt of the ſoules doe under the Altar) their re-uniting and joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning together again, and ſo conſequently the haſtning of the number of the elect, and ſecond comming of the Sonne of God to judgement.</p>
            <p>And thus much ſhall ſerve to be briefly ſpoken of the firſt expreſſion of the joyfulneſſe of their reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; that they ſhall <hi>Awake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come now unto the ſecond, where it is ſaid, that they ſhal <hi>Sing:</hi> And queſtionleſſe ſo they ſhal, and wee all ſhall ſing with them, whilſt the bleſſed Angels ſhall helpe to make up the quire: And good reaſon: for,</p>
            <p>Firſt, our worke is quite over, and all our toyle and labour ended, our field ploughed, and our vineyard planted; the Spring is come, and the voyce of the Turtle heard in our land;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.12</note> is it not fit then that wee ſhould ſing a <hi>Requiem</hi> to our ſoules.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our warfare is at an end, our enemies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:21508:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and loe our victorious Generall is mounted now on high, upon his triumphant Chariot, with innumerable troopes of Angels, and celeſtiall ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers upon his right hand, and upon his left ſetting forth his praiſe, ſhewing his noble acts, and ſinging his victory: what ſoule is there, that ever reaped comfort from the ſame, that inſtantly will not joyne it ſelfe with this joyfull aſſembly, and beare a part in this triumphant ſong,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.9.10.</note> ſaying with the reſt, <hi>Bleſsing, honor, glory, and power, be unto him that ſitteth on the Throne, and unto the Lambe for ever and ever. For thou haſt redeemed us by thy blood, and haſt made us unto God, Kings and Prieſts, and wee ſhall raigne on the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 It is the marriage day, wherein the eſpouſals betwixt Chriſt and his Church ſo long deferred, ſhall bee fully perfected, when the glorious Bride, (comming forth in a rich mantle al of white, which her beloved ſpouſe long before beſtowed on her) ſhall be married to her husband the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: who having crowned her with the crowne of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, wil take her into the Bride-chamber neere unto himſelfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.</note> and there ſhee ſhall abide for ever. If the <hi>Spheres</hi> (as ſome will have the) doe dayly moove in a moſt melodious ſort, then, queſtionleſſe wil they utter their chiefeſt &amp; moſt delightful tunes, and like ſo many roling Cymbals, ſerve that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Quire. Then will Heaven and Earth bee fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with <hi>Epithalamies,</hi> and ſongs of Love. Then ſhal we ſee (I doubt not) this ſweete young Gentleman, comming forth with his Laurell on his head,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.7</note> and his rich Robe on his backe, waſhed in the Blood of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:21508:42"/>
the Lambe, ſinging <hi>Alleluiahs</hi> unto God, and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the reſt, <hi>Let us be glad and reioyce, and give honour unto him, for the Lambe is come, and his Wife hath made her ſelfe ready.</hi> The conſideration whereof, ought to bee another maine comfort, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that ſadneſſe which the ſhadow of death brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth with it, when a darke cloud ſhall oppreſſe our hearts, when our ſonges ſhall be turned into heavy ſighes, and all our mirth into dolefull complaints: then let the Childe of God thus thinke with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; well, though I cannot now bee merry, yet the time is comming when I know I ſhall, now I am ſad, but then I ſhall ſing, my ſhip being entred the wiſhed Haven, and this boyſterous tempeſt wholly over.</p>
            <p>But I haſten to an end, intending as briefly as I can, to cloſe up all with the reaſon that the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Spirit yeeldeth in the latter end of the verſe: why the dead carkaſſes ſhall not onely ariſe, but in ſo beautifull alſo and joyfull a ſort: the which is no other, in word, then the opperative and working power, and vertue of the Reſurrection of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, being the ſame to the dead, that the dewe and ſappe in the ſpring, is to the hearbes and graſſe of the field. All the Winter long (expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience teacheth us) when ſnow and froſt covers the ground, the graſſe and plants of the earth appeare as dead and withered, untill the ſpring commeth, when a pleaſant dew armed with the power of the Sunne, not only mouldreth and prepareth the earth, but ſoaking downe unto the rootes of the plants, cauſeth them ſpeedily to ariſe and grow,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:21508:43"/>
ſo that within ſhort time after, the travailer may with their beauty feede his eye, and the Labourer with the Fruite of the ſame, fill his lap or boſome. All which the Spirit of God (in ſaying thy <hi>Dew is as the Dew of Hearbes, and the Earth ſhall give up her dead</hi>) intimateth to be the happy condition of all the Elect at the latter day. So that how ever their Bones bee drye, their Beauty loſt, and they returned agayne to Earth and Duſt, yet ſhall the fruite and benefite of the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, like an heavenly dew, or rather like the breath of GOD himſelfe, ſoake downe and pierce into the bottome of their Graves, cauſing them to ariſe and bloſome foorth, like the Roſe of the valley, and Lilly of the field, the darlings of the Spring; all which is by the finger of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And that the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of the Lord Ieſus ſhall doe all this;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6.4 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10 <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. <hi>Col.</hi> 6.4</note> may appeare both by multitude of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture, proving the trueth hereof, as alſo by ſo many exhortations which wee uſually meete withall, wherein wee are earneſtly put on to fit and prepare our ſelves for ſo high a dignity and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment amongſt others,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.6.8.</note> 1. <hi>Theſſalon.</hi> 5. where the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Apoſtle</hi> willeth us, <hi>Not to ſleepe as others doe, but but watch and bee ſober, putting on the breaſt plate of Faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.14</note> 
               <hi>and Love, and for our Helmet, the hope of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> And the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> in exhorting us (in his 1 <hi>Epiſtle</hi> 3.14.) ſo earneſtly as hee doth; that ſeeing wee looke for ſuch things to bee diligent, that <hi>wee may be found of him in peace, without ſpot or ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jud.</hi> 20.21</note> The like doth the holy <hi>Apoſtle</hi> Saint <hi>Iude,</hi> in the twenteth <hi>Chapter,</hi> and the twenteth firſt
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:21508:43"/>
               <hi>verſe</hi> of his Epiſtle, in this ſort, <hi>Wherefore my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, keepe your ſelves in the love of God, looking for the mercy of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt unto eternall Life.</hi> But if this I have ſpoken ſomething before, with which contenting my ſelfe, I will in a word or two and that very briefly, ſhew unto you, the reaſon of the compariſon, wherein the vertue of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Chriſt Ieſus is compared unto that dew of Hearbes. The which indeede doth moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently demonſtrate and expreſſe the nature of the ſame, as may appeare by theſe inſtances follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Dew deſcendeth from above whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wrought and perfected by thoſe ſuperiour bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; and is, as it were, the ſweat of their brows: ſuch ſurely and undoubtedly, is the vertue of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Chriſt, a Divine and caeleſtiall Dew, pleaſantly diſtilling and dropping downe from the ſacred top of that caeleſtiall <hi>Hermon</hi> at all times; but then chiefly and more eſpecially, when hee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looſeth and untyeth the ſorrows of Death; it beeing unpoſſible for it to hold him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Dew is of a mollifying and ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning nature (as I ſayd before) fitting the plants to ſpring, and the earth to bring foorth: ſuch is the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection</hi> of our bleſſed Saviour, of ſo powerfull and working a nature, leading things on, in ſo ſweete and excellent an order, to their ſeveral ends, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the hardneſſe and ſtubbornnes of the earth, the drineſſe and rottenneſſe of the trees, nor the indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the dead bodies themſelves ſhall hinder, but that the earth <hi>ſhall caſt up her dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:21508:44"/>Thirdly, the dew of hearbes is not onely full of ſpirits, and of a cheering and quickning nature, but likewiſe ſweete and pleaſant, caſting foorth a moſt odiferous ſcent and ſavour, (witneſſe our Gardens in the Spring mornings,) of ſuch both quickning and perfuming nature will the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt be, by meanes whereof, the Bodies of the Elect ſhall not onely bee reſtored to life againe, but the ſtinch and rotten ſavours of the Grave being remooved, they ſhalbee ſo ſweetned and perfumed with the odiferous ſavours of the ſame, that all their Garments ſhall ſmell of <hi>Myrrhe, Alloes,</hi> and <hi>Caſſia,</hi> together with all the choiſeſt ſpices of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, fitting the Ivory pallace whereinto they are to enter, and where they are to rejoyce for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the Dew is of a moſt beautifull and faire aſpect, gracing much the flowers, with her chriſtall droppes like ſo many orient pearles, dang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on the ſeverall ſlippes and ſprigs thereof: ſo ſurely will the vertue of the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> bee to all thoſe that are truely his, at his ſecond comming, which will be to judgement; beautify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and adorning them in a more rich and coſtly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then all the chaines, broaches, and ornaments on the earth poſſibly can do, yea paſt the apprehenſion of man.</p>
            <p>Sith then Brethren it is ſo, and the <hi>ſonne</hi> of God hath done all this for us, making by his owne <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection</hi> ours likewiſe, every way ſo certaine, and ſure, and every way ſo joyfull, let us then in time, I pray you, make ſure of the ſame, which beleeve
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:21508:44"/>
me, we may eaſily do, if we get but our part in the firſt Reſurrection. For if by the Reſurrection of Chriſt we be once rayſed out of the Grave of ſinne; then let us no way queſtion, but by the power of the ſame Reſurrection, wee ſhalbee likewiſe raiſed out of the bed and grave of corruption. Hence, ſayth the holy Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. <hi>verſe</hi> 14. <hi>Wee know that he that rayſed up the Lord Ieſus Chriſt: ſhall raiſe us up alſo by Ieſus, and ſhall preſent us with you:</hi> and <hi>bleſſed and happy are they</hi> (ſayth <hi>St. Iohn) that have a part in the firſt Reſurrection, for over them the ſecond death hath no part.</hi> And this likewiſe will appeare plainly unto us, if our mindes and affections be not, with the blind Mole, and bruitiſh Swine, grubling here below; but with the nimble and pleaſant wings of the Hawke and Eagle ſoaring daily, and mounting up on high, with all care and diligence ſeeking after thoſe celeſtial things that are above: according to which Rule, the bleſſed Apoſtle leadeth on his exhortation <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.1. after this manner: <hi>If you be ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen with Chriſt (ſayth hee) then ſeeke thoſe things that are above:</hi> as though hee ſhould ſay, if yee bee riſen with Chriſt, then ought you to ſeeke after the things that are above. And agayne, if you bee riſen with him, then you cannot but ſeeke after them: ſo then by this ſeeking, it may eaſily appeare whether wee be riſen with Chriſt; which if we be, then bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are wee; for the ſecond death ſhall have no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over us: But death ſhalbe to us the beginning of Life, and a happy paſſage for us, from an inferiour Roome, to an higher; from baſe <hi>Iericho,</hi> to that beautifull <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> that is above: whether ſtormes
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:21508:45"/>
and tempeſts cannot reach; and where the morning ſunne alwayes ſhineth; where Rivers of oyle runne guſhing up and downe; and where is the temple of the living God, and of the Lambe, where is Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, in which is no <hi>Serpent</hi> to tempt; or <hi>Death</hi> with his arrow to kill: where are Riches without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and glory without compariſon; where the day never endeth, nor comfort fadeth; where our mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſhall quite ceaſe, and wee keepe a perpetuall Sabboth, with the bleſſed Angels and ſoules of the Righteous: ſolacing our ſelves in the preſence of the bleſſed Trinity; and ſitting us downe at the right hand of the Father, where are pleaſures for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb facs="tcp:21508:45"/>
            <head>AN ELEGY UPON THE DEATH OF THE TRVLY NOBLE GEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TLEMAN, <hi>EDWARD LEWKENOR</hi> Eſquire, lamenting eſpecially the finall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of that worthy and (in other Countries) ancient Family although in <hi>Suffolke</hi> continued but for three Generations <hi>By</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Edward Lewknor,</hi> the Elder.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Edward Lewknor,</hi> the yonger.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edward Lewknor</hi> Eſquire.</item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ould I but ſing ſuch layes <hi>(great Soule)</hi> as thou</l>
            <l>Chant'ſt amongſt <hi>Angels,</hi> and <hi>Arch-Angels</hi> now;</l>
            <l>I might commend thee, but ſuch notes as ours,</l>
            <l>Are like<note n="*" place="margin">A Crow ſaluted <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus</hi> with theſe words: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve <hi>Caeſar. Mac. Stat.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 4</note> 
               <hi>Crowes Aves</hi> to <hi>great Emperors.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>A wonder, <hi>Reader,</hi> in one tombe doth lye</l>
            <l>Lowly <hi>interr'd</hi> a ſtately Family:</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21508:46"/>A greater yet; loe one poore heape of mould</l>
            <l>Holds <hi>three</hi> ſuch men, as ſcarſe a <hi>World</hi> can hold.</l>
            <l>Greateſt of all, but <hi>three Decents,</hi> compriſe</l>
            <l>More Worthies, then moſt long liv'd <hi>Families.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Even as great ſummes for moſt <hi>part greater grow</hi>
            </l>
            <l>By adding <hi>Cyphers,</hi> to the <hi>Figures;</hi> ſo,</l>
            <l>Tis oft in antique ſtemmes; wherin wee ſee</l>
            <l>Five or ſixe nulls, for one <hi>Poore vnity:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>But 't was not ſo in <hi>yours, Nature</hi> would not</l>
            <l>Set downe one <hi>Cypher,</hi> but all decades wrot.</l>
            <l>One old, in whom ten <hi>Neſtors</hi> did reſide:</l>
            <l>One middle aged, in whom there did abide</l>
            <l>The <hi>Worth,</hi> and <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> of as great a ten,</l>
            <l>As <hi>Nature</hi> breeds amongſt the ſonnes of men:</l>
            <l>One yong, whom now to Fate we would not grutch,</l>
            <l>If out of ten wee could extract one ſuch:</l>
            <l>Or as in counting, oft, we ſee no leſſe</l>
            <l>Then <hi>twenty Counters,</hi> layed downe to expreſſe</l>
            <l>Some Shillings, or <hi>Deniers;</hi> when two or three</l>
            <l>Doe Hundreds, thouſands, Millions ſignifie.</l>
            <l>So 'twas in you <hi>(Great Saints,) Nature</hi> had lay'd</l>
            <l>Her Millions, then her numbring hand ſhee ſtaid;</l>
            <l>Thinking perchance it were but vaine expence</l>
            <l>Of <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Art,</hi> to put downe pounds and pence:</l>
            <l>Had ſhe compoſed ſome fulſome potion,</l>
            <l>Some huge <hi>Gallenical</hi> decoction;</l>
            <l>Putting in ſubſtance, leaves and ſtalks, and all</l>
            <l>Boyl'd in ſome quarts of Liquor Phyſicall,</l>
            <l>You might have beene perchance a greater doſe,</l>
            <l>And match't the Stemme-proud vaſt Magnificoes;</l>
            <l>But, when our <hi>Paracelſian</hi> would extract</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Spirits, Spirit,</hi> ſo exact</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21508:46"/>As Quinteſſence it ſelfe compared to it,</l>
            <l>Was but <hi>Terrene</hi> and <hi>Feculent</hi> as yet;</l>
            <l>Her curious <hi>Alymbecke,</hi> would forth powre,</l>
            <l>Onely three drops, then ſtaid and would no more.</l>
            <l>As in <hi>Joves</hi> Pallace, the vaſt <hi>Firmament</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Shines with a many Starre-bright ornament,</l>
            <l>But ſuch as to the Gazers eye diſplay,</l>
            <l>Scarce any thing, but Buls and Rams, and gay</l>
            <l>Strumpets and Concubines, and Gorgons heads,</l>
            <l>Scorpions, and Centaures, and ten thouſand dreads;</l>
            <l>When as thoſe Orbes, wherein one <hi>Starre</hi> is fix't,</l>
            <l>Carry ſome God or Goddeſſe uncommix't</l>
            <l>With ugly formes; ſo was your deſtiny:</l>
            <l>Yee were all God-like men, although but <hi>Three:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>O ſacred number, though it had no more</l>
            <l>But yee to make it <hi>ſacred!</hi> Henceforth ſcore</l>
            <l>Amongſt the paternes of Triplicity:</l>
            <l>Holy <hi>triplicity;</hi> this bleſſed <hi>three,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And next the greateſt, let it greateſt be.</l>
            <l>Nor did the cruell fates their anger ſhew;</l>
            <l>But favour rather, to permit ſo few.</l>
            <l>Rare things are made, for one age to behold,</l>
            <l>Others to wonder at: If they grow old</l>
            <l>And common, al our admiration ſtints;</l>
            <l>So Loadſtones are ſcarce better deem'd then Flints:</l>
            <l>Which were they rare, no Gold or Orient<note n="*" place="margin">A round Loadſtone called <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rella.</hi>
               </note> ſtone,</l>
            <l>The great earth ſcarce, would buy the little one.</l>
            <l>'Tis not for every age of man to know,</l>
            <l>An <hi>Hector, Caeſar, Cato, Scipio;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>No, nor a <hi>Lewknor</hi> neither! 't may ſuffice,</l>
            <l>To ſee a <hi>Phoenix</hi> in five <hi>Centuries.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Yet may we ſee<note n="*" place="margin">Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Lewk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> in <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er,</hi> brother to Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Lewk<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nor</hi> the yonger.</note> one in another clime,</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21508:47"/>A Golden <hi>Branch, Tranſplanted;</hi> which no time</l>
            <l>Shall waſt; untill that faire ſtemme hath out wore,</l>
            <l>As many yeares as it had dayes before:</l>
            <l>And ſhall in thee<note n="*" place="margin">His one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> ſweet Babe, whom heaven hath lent</l>
            <l>Vnto the World, that having largely ſpent</l>
            <l>Such ſtore of Honour in thy <hi>Sire,</hi> by thee</l>
            <l>Another name may gaine like dignity;</l>
            <l>Amen to this, ſay al the Saints on high;</l>
            <l>Amen to this, be Angels Harmony:</l>
            <l>Say thou Amen, thou fountaine of al <hi>Store,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Thy ſaying's doing; ſay't wee aske no <hi>More:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Till then, live ſtill thou Bleſſed name, in<note n="*" place="margin">The La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Lewke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,</hi> wife to Sir <hi>Ed. Lewkenor</hi> the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</note> Thee</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Daughter, Wife, Mother,</hi> to this heavenly <hi>Three;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Relique of <hi>Three great</hi> Saints in Heaven, &amp; Mother</l>
            <l>To <hi>Three</hi> on earth unmatch't, but by their Brother.</l>
            <l>As Iron plac't betwixt two Loadſtones, loth</l>
            <l>To forſake either, hangs betwixt them both:</l>
            <l>So live t'wixt Heaven and Earth: and be thou hight</l>
            <l>An Earthly Angell, or an Heavenly wight;</l>
            <l>Vntill the Heavenly part made ſtrong by fate,</l>
            <l>Draw thee at laſt to thine Eternall ſtate.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <pb facs="tcp:21508:47"/>
            <head>AN EPITAPH.</head>
            <l>THe faireſt <hi>Bloſſome</hi> of as <hi>Faire</hi> a <hi>Tree</hi>
            </l>
            <l>As <hi>Suffolke</hi> yeelds, <hi>Reader,</hi> lyes vnder mee.</l>
            <l>'Tint ſtrange that Bloſſoms fade, but cruell Fate</l>
            <l>Did in this bud the whole <hi>Tree</hi> ruinate;</l>
            <l>A <hi>Tree tranſplanted</hi> hither, to diſplay</l>
            <l>A <hi>Wonder</hi> in each age, and then decay:</l>
            <l>For aged, middle, yong, come Fame and tell</l>
            <l>To <hi>three,</hi> but <hi>three Lewkenors,</hi> a paralell.</l>
            <l>Ar't mute? then let thy Trumpe their worth reſound,</l>
            <l>And fame reviue whom Fate hath layed in <hi>Ground,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And when one ſtemme, <hi>three Edwards</hi> can allot,</l>
            <l>Like unto theſe; let <hi>Lewkenor</hi> bee forgot.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOH. GARNONS. D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> D.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21508:48"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21508:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21508:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21508:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21508:51"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21508:51"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21508:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21508:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:21508:53"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21508:53"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21508:54"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:21508:54"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:21508:55"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21508:55"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:21508:56"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21508:56"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:21508:57"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:21508:57"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:21508:58"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21508:58"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:21508:59"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:21508:59"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:21508:60"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21508:60"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:21508:61"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:21508:61"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:21508:62"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:21508:62"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21508:63"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:21508:63"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21508:64"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:21508:64"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
